<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse concerning the witnesses, relating to the time, place, and manner of their being slain by William Hooke, late preacher of the Gospel.</title>
            <author>Hooke, William, 1600 or 1601-1678.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 157 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44326</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2622</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32034</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12298174</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12298174</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59095</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44326)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59095)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1505:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse concerning the witnesses, relating to the time, place, and manner of their being slain by William Hooke, late preacher of the Gospel.</title>
                  <author>Hooke, William, 1600 or 1601-1678.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Astwood for Thomas Cockeril ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Revelation --  Commentaries.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59095:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59095:1"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE CONCERNING The Witneſſes, Relating to the TIME, PLACE, and MANNER of their being Slain.</p>
            <p>BY <hi>WILLIAM HOOKE,</hi> late Preacher of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. Aſtwood,</hi> for <hi>Thomas Cockeril</hi> at the <hi>Three Legs</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey,</hi> over againſt the <hi>Stocks-Market,</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:59095:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:59095:2"/>
            <div n="1" type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt. I.</hi> Whether the Witneſſes are Slain?</head>
               <p>I Dare not be definitive and peremptory in making anſwer hereunto, being conſcious to much darkneſs in my ſelf about the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and unfolding matters Apocalyptical, and knowing alſo that there are many difficulties attending the Anſwer of this Queſtion; I ſhall therefore humbly lay before you what the Scripture ſpeaketh, and leave it to you to conſider and conclude as the Lord ſhall help you. And in order to what I ſhall ſay, there is ſomething that I would premiſe, and it is this: That in the ſlaughter of the Witneſſes there is that which carrieth a great analogy and proportion to the death of Chriſt, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration whereof will much help us in the Anſwer of the Queſtion; but I mean not a complete and adequate proportion, but as to many remar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable Particulars.</p>
               <p>The ſufferings of the Church are a great part of the ſubject matter of this Book of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> eſpecially under the Seals and Trumpers, till you come to the laſt Wo, which is objectated chiefly on Antichriſt: And theſe Sufferings were partly under the <hi>Pagan Roman</hi> Empire, partly under <hi>Rome Antichriſtian;</hi> and the ſufferings of the Saints under both are the ſufferings of Chriſt myſtical, and are ſo expreſſed as bearing a great proportion and likeneſs with the ſufferings of Chriſt perſonal.</p>
               <p>The firſt of theſe ſufferings of Chriſt myſtical we find, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.1, 2, 3. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> where it is ſaid, <hi>The Woman being with Child, cryed, travelling in Birth, and pained to be delivered.</hi> The Woman here is the Church, and the Child that ſhe travelleth with is her Seed, which is <hi>Chriſt myſtical,</hi> whoſe Sufferings by the great Red Dragon (<hi>i. e.</hi> the Devil in the <hi>Roman Pagan</hi> Empire) do, in many things,<note n="*" place="margin">Mr. <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> on Rev. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> as a Learned Interpreter hath ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, allude to the ſufferings of Chriſt perſonal when he was born.
<list>
                     <item>1. In that Chriſt was a Child born of a Woman under many outward wants, ſo as the condition of the Church is commonly.</item>
                     <item>2. In that <hi>Herod</hi> did watch to deſtroy Chriſt ſo loon as he was born, and as <hi>Paraoh</hi> (ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times called a Dragon) ſought to deſtroy the <hi>Jews</hi> Male-Children as ſoon as they came into the world.</item>
                     <item>3. As Chriſt when he was born, was ſoon put to flee into <hi>Aegypt</hi> with his Mother; ſo it is here with the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:59095:3"/>Church and her ſeed, they flee into the Wilderneſs.</item>
                     <item>4. The foreſaid Author affirmeth, that the time of Chriſts being in <hi>Aegypt</hi> was three years and an half, which (in the miſtery) is the time of the Church her Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs condition: For Chriſt (as my Author affirmeth) was born in the thirtieth year of <hi>Herods</hi> Reign, but he fled not preſently, but was firſt cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed and his Mother purified, after which alſo <hi>Herod</hi> ſought to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the young Children in and about <hi>Bethlehem:</hi> This took up ſome part of <hi>Herods</hi> thirty firſt year, and Chriſt returned out of <hi>Aegpyt</hi> immediately after <hi>Herods</hi> death, who reigned thirty four years.</item>
                     <item>5. As <hi>Herod</hi> vented his malice upon the <hi>Bethlehemitiſh</hi> Infants after the flight of Chriſt; ſo doth the Devil here vent his malice upon the Church her ſeed after her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance and flight.</item>
                     <item>6. As Chriſt was ſtill preſerved till he had finiſhed the work committed to him, notwithſtanding all the oppoſition he met with, but after that he ſuffered and was ſlain; even ſo it happeneth to the ſeed of the Church. Thus you ſee how the ſufferings of Chriſt myſtical under <hi>Rome Pagan,</hi> do in many things anſwer to the ſufferings of Chriſt perſonal.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, Let us conſider the other part of the ſufferings of Chriſt Myſtical under <hi>Rome Antichriſtian,</hi> and we ſhall ſee their conformity to the ſufferings of Chriſt Perſonal, eſpecially in and about his death.</p>
               <p>It is ſaid (you know)<note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 11.8.</note> 
                  <hi>that the doad Bodies of the Witneſſes ſhall lye in the Street of the great City, which is ſpiritually called</hi> Sodom <hi>and</hi> Aegypt, <hi>where alſo our Lord was crucified.</hi> Which laſt words are added, not only to diſcover under what power the Witneſſes ſhould be ſlain, <hi>viz.</hi> that of <hi>Rome, ſpiritually called</hi> Sodom <hi>and</hi> Aegypt; but alſo to ſhew us the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity that ſhould be between the ſlaughter of Chriſt and his Witneſſes. And yet we muſt not expect a complete analogy and proportion between them, for in ſome Circumſtances they differ, but in ſeveral material ones they do agree.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Chriſt preacheth forty two Months, literally taken; the witneſſes propheſie as long, taking forty two months<note n="*" place="margin">Numb. 14.34. Ezek. 4.6.</note> prophetically and myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally.</item>
                  <item>2. Chriſt is ſlain when he had finiſhed his Teſtimony, and could not by any means be ſlain before; ſo it is with the Witneſſes, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.7.</item>
                  <item>3. Chriſt is ſlain by the<note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 11.8. with Luk. 18.32 33.</note> 
                     <hi>Gentiles,</hi> grammatically and properly ſo ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; and the Witneſſes are ſlain by the<note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 11.2, 7.</note> 
                     <hi>Gentiles,</hi> metaphorically ſo taken.</item>
                  <item>4. Chriſt aroſe after three days, figuratively taken, <hi>i. e.</hi> part being put for the whole: His Witneſſes ariſe after three days and an half, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetically taken, <hi>i. e.</hi> three years and an half.</item>
                  <item>5. Chriſt's Sepulchre was guarded to keep him down in his Grave, and hinder his Reſurrection,<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 27.64.</note> which his enemies could not bear the thoughts
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:59095:3"/>of: In like manner the enemies of the Witneſſes endeavour to keep them down by power, and ſo to bury them (but that they are hindered) that they might never riſe again.</item>
                  <item>6. When Chriſt was crucified, preſently beginneth the <hi>Jews</hi> Paſſeover, where his Enemies rejoyced together and made merry, becauſe Chriſt, who had tormented them was crucified:<note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 11.10.</note> Even thus deal the Enemies of the Witneſſes when they are ſlain.</item>
                  <item>7. Chriſt aroſe notwithſtanding the Soldiers who guarded his Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre, and when he aroſe they were wofully skared at the ſight of him:<note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 11.11.</note> Even ſo it is at the Reſurrection of his Witneſſes.</item>
                  <item>8. When Chriſt aroſe there was a great Earthquake, properly ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: So, not long after the Reſurrection of the Witneſſes, there is<note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 11.13.</note> a great Earthquake, myſtically and metaphorically ſo called.</item>
               </list>
               <p>This Analogy thus premiſed, I ſhall expreſs to you what the Scripture ſaith concerning the ſlaughter of the Witneſſes, that you may make your Collections from it as the Lord ſhall help you.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The<note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.8, 9.</note> Text ſeemeth to hold forth ſuch a ſlaughter of the Witneſſes, as is partly civil and partly ſpiritual: For were the ſlaughter literal and proper, the enemies of the Witneſſes would not have endured their dead Bodies to have lyen ſo long unburied in the Street, becauſe of the noiſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs thereof; nor would Kindreds, and Tongues, and Nations have hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered their burial, from the Principle of mere Humanity. And therefore this their death muſt be of another kind, and that is partly civil, the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes being deprived of their liberty and free exerciſe of their Religion by humane Laws and Conſtitutions; whereupon their death becomes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo partly ſpiritual, in that their Spirits faint and fail ſo far, that they are bereft of ſpiritual Life and Courage; the ſpirit of Life is greatly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn from them, and they are poſſeſſed with great fear and faintneſs. And that this is the manner of their death, appeareth, in that upon their Reſurrection it is ſaid, that <hi>the ſpirit of life from God entred into them,</hi> which clearly ſignifieth, that during their ſlaughter, they were deprived of ſpiritual life and activity. You ſee then what kind of death this of the Witneſſes is, partly <hi>civil</hi> and partly <hi>ſpiritual, civil</hi> as to the outward means, ſlaying, <hi>ſpiritual</hi> as to the inward man, ſlain.</p>
               <p>And if it be thus, then we are not to account the great ſlaughter of the Saints in other Countries, <hi>viz. Germany, Holland, France, Piedmont, England</hi> in thoſe <hi>Marian</hi> days, to be this ſlaughter of the Witneſſes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thoſe ſlaughters were properly ſuch in a literal ſence, and the Saints ſo ſlain were buried in a proper ſence.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Text telleth us,<note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 11.7.</note> that the Witneſſes muſt finiſh (or be in fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing)
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:59095:4"/>their Teſtimony, before they can be ſlain; that is, they muſt be finiſhing it,
<list>
                     <item>1. As to the time or period of their propheſying, <hi>viz.</hi> at the end of 1260 years, a day being put for a year.</item>
                     <item>2. As to the matter of their Teſtimony, or the thing to be witneſſed by them.</item>
                  </list> And therefore begin the <hi>Epocha</hi> and riſe of their Propheſying where you will, you fail in the commencement thereof, if the 1260 years do not determine and conclude in the finiſhing of the matter of the Teſtimony, which is to be inſiſted upon as much as the period and concluſion of it. And from hence again I gather, that all your former ſlaughters in other Countries, cannot be that mentioned here, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.7. becauſe the Teſtimony of <hi>Jeſus</hi> was not materially finiſhed in any of them, no nor in finiſhing.</p>
               <p>When therefore is this Teſtimony finiſhed,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> as to the matter of it?</p>
               <p>When the whole Office of Chriſts Mediatorſhip is teſtified unto; that is, not only his Prophetical and Prieſtly, but alſo his Kingly Office, When Antichriſt wrought, as it were under ground, during the ſounding of the four firſt Trumpets, he oppoſed the Perſon of Chriſt by thoſe ancient blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous hereſies of the <hi>Arrians, Neſtorians, Eutichyans, Macedonians, &amp;c.</hi> But ſince the ſounding of the firſt Wo-Trumpet, he hath more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially oppoſed his Mediatorſhip, which the Witneſſes have ſtill aſſerted to this day. And this Teſtimony of theirs muſt be complete, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable alſo to that of Chriſt himſelf, who finiſhed his Teſtimony<note n="*" place="margin">1 Tim. 6.13.</note> when he witneſſed a good Confeſſion before <hi>Pontius Pilate:</hi> And what was that Confeſſion? You may ſee in <hi>Joh.</hi> 18.33-38. where he aſſerteth and avoucheth his Spiritual Kingdom before the <hi>Roman</hi> Governor, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he finiſhed his Teſtimony; for he was put to death upon that very ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, as appeareth hereby; in that when <hi>Pilate</hi> ſaid unto the <hi>Jews,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Joh. 19.6, 7, 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Take ye him and crucifie him, for I find no fault in him:</hi> Say the <hi>Jews, We have a law, and by our Law he ought to die, becauſe he made himſelf the Son of God.</hi> I ſay, this did not move <hi>Pilate</hi> at all, but rather affright him from medling with Chriſt, and cauſe him to attempt his releaſe; for Chriſt muſt not die upon the confeſſion only of his <hi>Perſon,</hi> that he was the Son of God.</p>
               <p>When the <hi>Jews</hi> therefore perceived that this would not prevail with <hi>Pilate,</hi> they cryed out, ſaying: <hi>If thou let this man go, thou art nor</hi> Caeſars <hi>Friend; whoſoever maketh himſelf a King, ſpeaketh againſt</hi> Caeſar. Ay, now <hi>Pilate</hi> is put hard to it, and ſits down again upon his Judgment-Seat, and ſaith to the <hi>Jews, Behold your King:</hi> But they cried out, <hi>Away with him, away with him, Crucifie him: Pilate</hi> ſaith unto them, <hi>Shall I crucifie your King? The Chief Prieſts anſwered, We have no King but</hi> Caeſar. <hi>Then</hi> Pilate <hi>delivered him to be Crucified.</hi> The <hi>Jews</hi> were weary enough, as we know, of the <hi>Roman</hi> Yoke, and had no cordial zeal for <hi>Caeſar,</hi> ſave only when he comes into competition with Chriſt, who muſt dye upon
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:59095:4"/>the point of his Kingly Power and Government, where his Teſtimony was finiſhed. And upon the ſame Confeſſion, muſt the Teſtimony of his Witneſſes be completed. And hence, again, I conclude, that all the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſlaughters in other Countries, cannot be (upon this very account) the ſlaughter of the Witneſſes ſpoken of, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.7—becauſe thoſe that ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, dyed not upon this Confeſſion.</p>
               <p n="3">3. When the Witneſſes are ſlain, it is the act of the Beaſt, as the ſame Text tells us: which word <hi>Beaſt,</hi> as applyed to Antichriſt, you ſhall ſometimes find mentioned in the <hi>Revelations,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.1, 4, with 11.</note> as diſtinct from the two horned Lamb that ſpeaks like a Dragon;<note n="†" place="margin">Rev. 17.7.</note> ſometimes you will find the Beaſt diſtinguiſhed from the Woman that ſits upon him;<note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 16.13. &amp; 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> another time you will find him diſtinguiſhed from the falſe Prophet. And when you find it thus, then by the <hi>Beaſt</hi> we are to underſtand the ſecular power of Antichriſt; and by the two horned Lamb, the Woman, and the falſe Prophet, we are to underſtand his Eccleſiaſtical. But when we find the word <hi>Beaſt</hi> mentioned alone, as it is in the ſlaughter of the Witneſſes, then it holds forth his complex Power, both Civil and Eccleſiaſtical. This being ſo, you here find this complicated Power of the <hi>Beaſt</hi> in the ſlaughter of the Witneſſes, who muſt be ſlain by both theſe Powers. And though the Eccleſiaſtical is included in the word <hi>Beaſt,</hi> when it ſtands alone; yet the Secular Power hath the preheminence therein: For it may ſo fall out, that when the Witneſſes are to be ſlain, there may not be ſo much power in the High Prieſt and his Followers, as to do it of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; their former Power, perhaps, may be diminiſhed, inſomuch that they muſt crave the help of the ſecular Officers to perform this work for them, like as the chief Prieſt and Elders did of <hi>Pilate;</hi> and this civil pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er muſt exert it ſelf, and make Laws and Decrees for the ſlaughter of the Witneſſes. It is therefore the Civil or Secular Power (implyed here more immediately in the <hi>Beaſt</hi>) that muſt commit this ſlaughter. True, the earneſt Votes, fervent Affections, and utmoſt Endeavours of the two horned Lamb, the ſcarlet Whore, and falſe Prophet, will be found in this Slaughter, as the Eccleſiaſtical Power was acceſſary to the killing of Chriſt Perſonal; but as it was <hi>Pilate</hi>'s Secular Power that ſtruck the great ſtroke; ſo muſt the Secular Power be eſpecially the Inſtrument in the death of the Witneſſes.</p>
               <p n="4">4. There muſt be a<note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 11.7.</note> particular, eminent and ſignal War waged with the Witneſſes by the Beaſt, when they are to be ſlain.</p>
               <p>For there is a clear diſtinction between the <hi>Beaſts</hi> war with the Saints, and his war with the Witneſſes when they are to be overcome and killed by him. As for his war with the Saints, it commenced with the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:59095:5"/>of his Reign, as is apparent, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.4-8. And this war runneth through the whole Reign of the <hi>Beaſt</hi> unto the very time that the Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes have finiſhed their Teſtimony; after which there<note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 11.7.</note> beginneth a diſtinct particular war with them; otherwiſe why is it ſaid, <hi>That when they have finiſhed their Teſtimony, the Beaſt that aſcendeth out of the bottomleſs pit, ſhall make war with them, overcome them, and kill them?</hi> For it may be ſaid, the <hi>Beaſt</hi> hath been at war with the Saints ever ſince he firſt aroſe. True; but this laſt war of his with the Witneſſes, is more particular, eminent and ſignal, as directed eſpecially againſt them, and not generally againſt all the Saints, as his former wars were, by which he roſe ſtill higher and higher, whereas after this particular and laſt war of his with the Witneſſes, he deſcendeth, and falls ſtill lower and lower, whereof I ſhall ſpeak more hereafter. By his firſt wars<note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 13.7.</note> he got power over Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds, Tongues, and Nations; whereas when he hath ſlain the Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, the Kindreds, and Tongues, and Nations ſhall diſlike his doings, and hinder his attempts to bury them.</p>
               <p>It being thus, hence it will follow, that in this laſt war, the Miniſters of the Goſpel, and the Churches (<note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 11.3, 4.</note> who are properly the Witneſſes) muſt be the ſpecial object of the Beaſts oppoſition. As for the reſt of the Saints, they ſhall eſcape this civil ſlaughter, that is, they ſhall fare bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the enemy ſhall not fight with ſmall nor great, ſave only with the Witneſſes; I mean, the heat of the Battel ſhall fall eſpecially upon them, they ſhall be ſadly handled, others ſhall not be ſo ſtrictly looked after, the weapons of the Adverſary, <hi>viz.</hi> his Edicts, Mulcts, Fines, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, Menaces, Searchings, Apprehenſions, Reſtraints, Confinements, Impoveriſhments, Baniſhments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are principally directed againſt them; they ſhall be ſought after and carried away, when others ſhall bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter eſcape. So that this war (you ſee) is diſtinct from that general long laſting war againſt the Saints ſpoken of in the thirteenth Chapter.</p>
               <p>But are not all the people of God Witneſſes,<note place="margin">Queſt.</note> eſpecially when they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs and practiſe againſt the <hi>Beaſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> in a large ſence, but not in the ſtrict meaning of the word in this eleventh Chapter. And among all the Saints, the Martyrs of <hi>Jeſus</hi> may beſt be called Witneſſes, for ſo the word ſignifieth; but the Witneſſes that we have here to do with, are (as I humbly conceive from the Text) Miniſters and Churches of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The Witneſſes muſt be ſlain,<note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 11.2.</note> not in the <hi>ſtreets,</hi> but <hi>ſtreet</hi> of that great City; that is, not in all places under the power and dominion of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> but in ſome one particular Province or Nation, which hath not (at leaſt fully) caſt off and renounced his Intereſt.</p>
               <p>It muſt be ſuch a Nation in which Jeſus Chriſt doth not Reign viſibly,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:59095:5"/>but the Government thereof is ſubſervient to the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> at leaſt as to the end and iſſue of the work, if not alſo as to the intention and ſcope of the workers. And yet it is not totally immers'd in Popery, becauſe there is a plentiful Teſtimony therein given againſt it, elſe how ſhould the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes be ſlain therein?</p>
               <p>But what <hi>Street</hi> may this be?<note place="margin">Queſt.</note>
               </p>
               <p>I will not define particularly; only it is ſome remarkable <hi>Street,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Anſw.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>&amp;c.</note> an Article, in the Original, prefixed to it, as much as to ſay, <hi>that Street.</hi> And when this <hi>Street</hi> is afterward mentioned under the notion of the tenth part of the City, both the tenth part and the City have this Article of Eminency ſet before them: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; <hi>Ver.</hi> 13. Now it is eminent either in relation to the Witneſſes that have formerly lived in it, and eſpecially that live in it immediately before the Slaughter; <hi>i. e.</hi> It muſt be a Nation eminent for its Teſtimony againſt the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and for its Teſtimony for Jeſus Chriſt and his Kingly Power in and over the Churches, which is the ſpecial matter of their Teſtimony for which they are ſlain; or elſe it is eminent, as belonging to the <hi>Beaſt</hi> in a ſpecial man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. And in both theſe reſpects (as ſaith a worthy and learned Writer) this <hi>Street</hi> is no other but <hi>Germany:</hi> But I do rather fix upon the firſt of theſe reſpects, becauſe that <hi>Teſtimony</hi> is the point upon which the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes are ſlain, and no other eminency can be found in the Text; though peradventure, there may be ſome other Countrey beſides <hi>Germany,</hi> which hath been very eminent for its relation to the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and which hath af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded him no ſmall revenue and ſupport.</p>
               <p>It therefore concerneth us to conſider, what Countrey and Nation hath been moſt eminent for its Teſtimony for Jeſus Chriſt and his complete Mediatorſhip: For though <hi>Germany</hi> hath been famous for its Witneſſes, in their generations, yet the eminency of the Witneſſes muſt lye, not in the number of them that give the Teſtimony, but eſpecially in the clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and completeneſs of the Teſtimony given; I ſay, <hi>The Street</hi> muſt excell in that reſpect, which will not be found in <hi>Germany,</hi> but rather in ſome other Country, in which the Kingly Power of Chriſt in and over his Churches, hath been teſtifyed both by Doctrine and Practice; and if you can find out that, you have found the <hi>Street.</hi> And, peradventure, when you have found it, you may find alſo that ſuch a <hi>Street</hi> may better brook the Prophetical and Prieſtly Offices of Chriſt, than his Kingly Power and Government: I ſay, <hi>better,</hi> though you may not find a full and cordial approbation of either; but as touching the Kingly Office of Chriſt, that will in no wiſe be admitted, but pertinaciouſly rejected, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this apprehenſion, that Chriſt and <hi>Caeſar</hi> cannot conſiſt,<note n="*" place="margin">Joh. 18.36.</note> though Chriſt hath ſaid the contrary; but the pride of man will not endure it.</p>
               <p>You ſee, partly, what a <hi>Street</hi> it muſt be in which the Witneſſes muſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:59095:6"/>be ſlain. And by this you may further ſee (by the way) what it is in Reformations, not to make through work: For ſuch a Street (I conceive) it will be, that is not diſcharged from ſubjection to the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> but is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervient to his Intereſt, though it may not be profeſſedly cordial to him. But what then is it, you will ſay, not to go through ſtitch with Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? It greatly gratifieth the Devil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> who, when he ſeeth that there is ſtill a remnant of Idolatry and Superſtition unpurged, preſently he markes uſe of that for the continuance of that perſecution which before was ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon other Cau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, which are now removed by a partial Reformation. For ſuch a perſecution muſt neceſſarily be in ſuch a Nation, or elſe how could the Witneſſes be ſlain there? So dangerous and dreadful a thing it is, not to do as <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>holad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> did after the death of that wicked woman <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liah;</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Kings 11.18.</note> for he cauſed the people <hi>to break the Altars and Images of</hi> Baal <hi>in picces thorowly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But (to return) the Witneſſes you ſee muſt be ſlain, not in the <hi>Streets,</hi> but <hi>Street, i. e.</hi> in ſome one remarkable Country under the power of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and which hath not caſt off his Government, though yet there muſt be ſo much of Proteſtancy, and Teſtimony againſt Papal Uſurpations and Impoſitions, and for the Kingly Power of Chriſt in and over his Churches, as will be a fit object for Perſecution even unto the ſlaughter of the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes.</p>
               <p>I know there are ſuch as like not to have this ſlaughter ſo narrowly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined, whereas the Text is expreſs for ſome particular <hi>Street;</hi> And there ſeemeth to me to be reaſon for it, why it ſhould be thus limited.
<list>
                     <item>1. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe if the ſlaughter ſhould be in all the <hi>Streets</hi> of the great City, <hi>i. e.</hi> in all the Countries under the power of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> there would be a very large Teſtimony, and the Witneſſes would be numerous, who (in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of their paucity)<note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 11.3.</note> are here ſaid to be two. For the Teſtimony muſt be but little and narrow when the Witneſſes are ſlain, as it was never very large before.</item>
                     <item>2. If they were to be ſlain in all Countries where the <hi>Beaſt</hi> hath to do, where ſhould we find thoſe <hi>Kindreds, Tongues, and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> that muſt hinder their Burial? For as concerning theſe hinderers, they ſeem to be a middle ſort of people, ſuch as neither like the ſlaughter of the Witneſſes, nor yet are full for the Teſtimony of the ſlain; but are of a mungrel kind, and ſtirr'd up by a worldly intereſt to hinder the Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial of the <hi>Witneſſes.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>They aim not herein at Reformation, nor at the exalting of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Government of Chriſt in the Churches, according to the rule of the everlaſting Goſpel, but are wholly ſwayed herein by Principles of State. Now I ſay, if the Witneſſes were to be ſlain in all places under the <hi>Beaſts</hi> Dominion, where ſhould we find out ſo many Kindreds, Tongues, and Nations, ſo and ſo qualified, as might ſuffice to hinder the Buryal of the Witneſſes?</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:59095:6"/>
               <p>Again; That it is not to be a general ſlaughter in all Countries, but only in ſome one particular, here called <hi>the Street,</hi> I ſhall demonſtrate by a further Argument.</p>
               <p>In order hereunto, we muſt know, that this <hi>Street</hi> is that which in <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.13. is called <hi>the tenth part of the City;</hi> for that Verſe is coupled with the precedent, as belonging to the ſame Story of the Death, Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Aſcenſion of the Witneſſes, and as<note n="*" place="margin">Vindicta divina d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtium ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is. <hi>Piſc.</hi> in <hi>Rev. 11.13.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Piſcator</hi> obſerveth, there is expreſſed in it, <hi>the revenge of God upon the enemies of the Witneſſes,</hi> and I cannot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee how it ſhould be otherwiſe underſtood. Hence then I thusargue:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Where the revenge of God is inflicted for the ſlaying of the Witneſſes, there (and there only) are the Witneſſes ſlain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But the revenge of God is inflicted only upon the tenth part of the City for the ſtaying of the Witneſſes; therefore in that tenth part only are they ſlain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the God of Revenges, in the execution of Judgment for ſuch and ſuch ſins, doth not exceed the limits of the Place and Perſons offending; he will not puniſh the Innocent for the ſins of the Delinquent, nor one Place for the iniquity of another. And yet I cannot but ſay, that the whole City is vertually guilty of this ſlaughter, as being not only guilty of the like, but alſo as approving of this. But God hath<note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 16.18.</note> another gueſs Earthquake in ſtore for the whole City, (<hi>i. e.</hi> the whole Papal Dominion) which ſhall deſtroy it all totally and for ever. This Earthquake (<hi>Rev.</hi> 11.13.) reacheth only the tenth part.</p>
               <p>I might further enlarge upon this point (which is of great moment as to the purpoſe in hand) by paſing through the ſeveral <hi>Streets</hi> of the great City, and rationally conſidering which of them is moſt likely to commit this Martyricide, as I may call it; eſpecially weighing withal what the Teſtimony muſt be upon which the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> muſt be ſlain, <hi>viz.</hi> Such as aſſerteth and exalteth the Kingly Power of Chriſt in his Churches, as you heard but now in the ſecond particular.</p>
               <p>Now this being granted, that the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> muſt be ſlain in ſome one particular and eminent Street, and not in all the whole Dition and Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the <hi>Beaſt;</hi> it will follow, that the former ſlaughters which have been committed in many Countries, and near about the ſame time, are not the ſlaughters that we are here enqui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing into. For I have read of many hundred of thouſands ſlain in ſeveral Countries for the Teſtimony of Je<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us, about the year 1540. and afterward for ſome years; but
<list>
                     <item>1. They were ſlain in a proper ſence.</item>
                     <item>2. Not upon the point of the Kingly Power of Chriſt; and therefore the Teſtimony was not finiſhed when they were ſlain.</item>
                     <item>3. Their dead Bodies were buried, nor did any hinder it.</item>
                     <item>4. They have lyen dead above an hundred years, and are not like to riſe again till
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59095:7"/>the Reſurrection at Chriſts coming; whereas, if the death of the Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes is proper, ſo muſt alſo their Reſurrection be.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. When the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> are ſlain, they muſt be looked upon by their enemies, as it were naturally dead, ſo dead in law, as if they were alſo dead in body. This may be gathered from <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.8, 9, 10. For the Kindreds, Tongues, and Nations, could not ſo look upon them, if their enemies did not ſo behold them; nor could their dead Bodies lye dead in the Street, and their enemies there living not look upon them; nor would the dwellers upon earth rejoyce and make merry at their death, did they not account them ſo dead, as that they would never riſe again; for did they but fear their Reſurrection, it would marr their mirth, as the Hand Writing on the Wall did <hi>Belſhazzar</hi>'s; becauſe if the Witneſſes did torment them before they were ſlain, O how would they excruciate them to the very death, ſhould they but riſe again! And hence it is, that their enemies will not be contented with the death of the <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept alſo they be buried, and therefore they attempt their interment, but that they are therein hindred: ſo that this attempt to bury them is not out of any love to them, but merely out of hatred, fearing leſt they ſhould riſe from the dead; for they will never think them dead enough. To this end, they will make one Law after another, and throw upon the ſlain Witneſſes one Edict after another, as they do upon dead Bodies when they throw one ſhovel-full of earth after another, ſaying, <hi>Earth to Earth, Aſhes to Aſhes, &amp;c.</hi> only not <hi>in ſure and certain hope of the Reſurrection</hi> of the Witneſſes <hi>to life</hi> again. And this multiplying of Laws upon them, is (interpretatively) their attempt to bury them.</p>
               <p n="7">7. There ſhall be no humane help, nor Arm of Fleſh imployed in their Reſurrection, this ſhall be wrought only by the Spirit of Life from God entring into them: <hi>Not by might, nor by power, but by my Spirit, ſaith the Lord.</hi> If any liberty ſhould be procured by force (which ought not to be) it will not proſper, nor will any attempts that way. The Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> ſhall be like a Reſurrection, wrought only by the om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent hand of Heaven, even by him in whoſe power alone it is to raiſe the dead, and to call things that are not as though they were. It is true indeed, when the Earthquake cometh, which followeth ſoon after the Aſcenſion of the Witneſſes, there will be great Concuſſions in that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, whatever it is, where the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> muſt be ſlain; but who ſhall be the Authors of them and Actors in them, I do not know; but as for the Reſurrection it ſelf, it ſhall be effected immediately by the Spirit of Life from God, who will certainly blaſt all humane attempts by Conſpiracies and Inſurrections in order (or rather diſorder) to the Reſurrection of the <hi>Witneſſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:59095:7"/>
               <p>Men were as good go about the raiſing of the dead out of their Graves, as to raiſe the ſlain Witneſſes by humane endeavours. When the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites were e'en upon the point of their Reſurrection out of <hi>Egypt</hi> (which was not complete till they aroſe out of the <hi>Red Sea; Ex.</hi> 15. compared with <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.2, 3.) what ſaith <hi>Moſes</hi> to them?<note n="*" place="margin">Exod. 14.13, 14.</note> 
                  <hi>Fear not, ſtand ſtill and ſee the ſalvation of God—The Lord ſhall fight for you, and ye ſhall hold your peace.</hi> And yet the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> at that time were<note n="†" place="margin">Exod. 13.18.</note> harneſſed, marſhalled, and prepared with Arms; and they uſed them not long after this their Reſurrection<note n="*" place="margin">Exod. 17.9.13.</note> againſt the <hi>Amalekites</hi> at <hi>Rephidim;</hi> but at their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection there muſt not be a Sword drawn, nor a ſtroke ſtruck; but as <hi>Jahaziel</hi> ſaid to <hi>Jehoſaphat</hi> and the men of <hi>Judah,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">2 Chr. 20.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Ye ſhall not need to fight in this Battel, ſet your ſelves, ſtand ye ſtill and ſee the ſalvation of the Lord with you.</hi> Thus (ſhould I live to the Time, and in the Street of the Reſurrection of the <hi>Witneſſes</hi>) would I ſay, and as <hi>Moſes</hi> alſo ſaid to the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> (who would needs go up uncalled, and fight againſt the <hi>Canaa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites,</hi>)<note n="*" place="margin">Numb. 14.41.</note> 
                  <hi>Wherefore now do ye tranſgreſs the Commandment of the Lord? But it ſhall not proſper; Go not up, for the Lord is not among you, that ye be not ſmitten before your enemies:</hi> Yet they would preſume and go up, but the <hi>Amalekites</hi> and <hi>Canaanites</hi> ſmote them and diſcomfited them even unto <hi>Hormah.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Ex. 17.</note> When they had a call to fight againſt the <hi>Amalekites,</hi> they conquered them; but when they will fight with them uncalled, they are ſmitten by them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Queſt. II.</hi> VVhat if we ſhould ſee ſuch a Slaughter, as ſymbolizeth much with that here, <hi>ver. 7, 8, &amp;c.</hi> And yet when the three years and half are ended, there appeareth little or nothing in view, agreeable to ſuch a Reſurrection as the Text here holdeth forth, <hi>ver. 11, 12?</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Anſw.</p>
               <p>HEre lyeth the difficulty, that (as I ſaid in anſwer to the former Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion the laſt time) I dare not be poſitive in determining whether the Witneſſes are ſlain or not; only I laid before you what the Scripture
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:59095:8"/>ſaith concerning their ſlaughter, and left it to you to conſider: And the ſame courſe I ſhall take at preſent in anſwer to this Queſtion.</p>
               <p>But before I come to the Anſwer, I ſhall premiſe a Poſition or two.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That there muſt not only be a Reſurrection of the ſlain Witneſſes, but ſuch a Reſurrection al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o as is here deſcribed, for the Scripture cannot be broken. It is not enough that there is an anſwerableneſs of things in the death of the Witneſſes, to prove their Slaughter; but there muſt be the like in their Reſurrection alſo, or we can conclude nothing. Every Slaughter hath not been <hi>the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nght<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r,</hi> and ſo every Reſurrection is not <hi>that Reſurrection;</hi> And to hold forth that which is like the death of the Witneſſes, but to fall in the Reſurrection, will not amount to ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This Reſurrection of the Witheſſes muſt be homogeneal, and of the ſame kind with the Slaughter, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> If the ſlaughter be partly civil and partly ſpiritual. ſo muſt alſo the Reſurrection be, and not proper and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teral; for thoſe Bodies can never riſe from a natural death, which were never deprived of their natural lives. Theſe Poſitions premiſed, I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to the Anſwer.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Negatively, I ſhall not anſwer as ſome have done, who ſay, that after three days and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the witneſſes ſhall ariſe, but how ſoon after it is not ſaid. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> not anſwer thus, for this were <hi>ponere Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectionem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſmite Reſurrection,</hi> without an, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of time; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o to what purpoſe would the Text in hand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rve? Or what comfort thould we have from it more than this, that there ſhall come a time when the witneſſes ſhall ariſe? For as <hi>Martha</hi> ſaid to Chriſt, of her dead Brother <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, I know that he ſhall ariſe again i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection at the laſt day;</hi> all her doubt was, whether Chriſt would raiſe him then, <hi>John</hi> 11.24. Even <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o might we ſay of the ſlain Witneſſes, if their Reſurrection here had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> been mentioned at all, <hi>We know that they ſhall riſe again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>:</hi> yea, but when ſhall they ariſe? After three days and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> half, ſaith the Text; therefore the time is determined. For in theſe words there is the <hi>Ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>inal or beginning of time from whence the Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urrection doth commerce and proceed, <hi>i. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> preſently after the expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the ſaid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of their death. For the time of their Witneſſing had,
<list>
                     <item>1. Its <hi>Epo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                              <desc>••••</desc>
                           </gap>,</hi> though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> dark and difficult to diſcover it.</item>
                     <item>2. Its Continuance, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </item>
                  </list>
like manner the time of their ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hath.
<list>
                     <item>1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>egi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ning, and term from whence to reckon; and</item>
                     <item>2. Its <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>ance, <hi>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>z.</hi> three years and an half: And ſhall not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ction alſo have a certain fixed beginning?</item>
                  </list> God is very pun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> as to his times and ſeaſons, though our dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:59095:8"/>knows not how to diſcern it, as you may ſee, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.40, 41, 42. It came to paſs at the end of the 430 years, even the ſelf ſame day it came to paſs, that all the hoſts of the Lord went out from the Land of <hi>Egypt:</hi> It is a night to be much obſerved, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> it is doubled and trebled to ſhew us Gods exactneſs in keeping time.</p>
               <p n="2">2. I ſhall not anſwer according to that Notion of ſome others concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing three years and half, <hi>i. e.</hi> three years (ſay they) and half three years for the words in the Original are theſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>i. e.</hi> ſay they, <hi>after three days and half,</hi> leaving out the word <hi>an;</hi> ſo that they reckon the time to be three years and half three years, <hi>i. e.</hi> four years and an half. But this anſwer will not hold: For,
<list>
                     <item>1. There are three notable Numbers in the <hi>Revelations,</hi> relating to the ſufferings of the Church, <hi>viz.</hi> 1260 days, and 42 months; and time, times, and half a time, <hi>i. e.</hi> three years and an half: For ſo many days are ſo many months, and ſo many months are ſo many years, a day being put for a year; ſo that there is a ſingular anſwerableneſs in theſe numbers, and therefore if we extend the three days and an half (<hi>i. e.</hi> three years and an half) to four years and an half, we break the proportion and correſpondence that is between theſe three numbers.</item>
                     <item>2. How will this notion hold, if at the end of four years and an half, there ſhould be no more ſhew of a Reſurrection, than there was at the end of three years and an half? I come therefore to an Affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Anſwer.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt. There are ſeveral Reſurrections mentioned in the Scriptures.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. The Reſurrection of the Soul from the death of Sin to the life of Grace, <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 5.25. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.1.</item>
                  <item>2. The Reſurrection of the Body at the coming of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.16. And the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e two Reſurrections are <hi>in inſtanti,</hi> or in a very ſhort and quick time, as it is ſaid of that great change, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.52. <hi>In th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>twink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. There is the Reſurrection of the <hi>Jews</hi> at their Converſion, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>for ſo it is calied, <hi>Ez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>k.</hi> 37.12, 13, 14. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.15.</item>
                  <item>4. The Reſurrection of the Witneſſes in my Text. And theſe two laſt are not ſo peedy as the two former, but have their gradual Proceſs and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ral <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ucceeding ſteps. For, as touching that of the Calling or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ws.</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. There is a noiſe.</item>
                        <item>2. A ſhaking.<note place="margin">Ezek. 37.7.-11.</note>
                        </item>
                        <item>3. A com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together of Bone to Bone.</item>
                        <item>4. Sinews and Fleſh coming upon them, and skin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ing them.</item>
                        <item>5. The breath of Life coming into them.</item>
                        <item>6. Their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> upon their feet as an exceeding great Army.</item>
                     </list>
So for the raiting of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>:
<list>
                        <item>1. The Spirit of Life from God entreth into them.</item>
                        <item>2. They fraud upon their feet.</item>
                        <item>3. They hear a great voice from Heave, ſaying, <hi>Come up hither.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:59095:9"/>
               <p>Secondly, I anſwer, that the Reſurrection of the Witneſſes ſeems to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the coming of the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> our of <hi>Egypt,</hi> for ſpiritual <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon</hi> is called ſpiritual <hi>Egypt, ver.</hi> 8. Which Deliverance was a kind of Reſurrection, as appears from the reſemblance there made to <hi>Abraham</hi> in a viſion, <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.9, 10, 11. Now the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> aroſe our of their bondage by degrees, for their Reſurrection was not complete till they roſe out of the <hi>Red Sea,</hi> and ſang the ſong of <hi>Moſes, Ex.</hi> 15. For till then they were not quite free from the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>yptians.</hi> They made ſeveral ſteps out of <hi>Egypt</hi> to the other ſide of the <hi>Red Sea, viz.</hi> from <hi>Rameſes</hi> to <hi>Succoth,</hi> from <hi>Succoth</hi> to <hi>Etham,</hi> from <hi>Etham</hi> to <hi>Pihahireth,</hi> from <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hiroth</hi> to the <hi>red Sea, Numb.</hi> 33.5-9. And therefore that remarkable day ſpoken of, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.40, 41, 42. is not to be underſtood of <hi>Iſraels</hi> complete Reſurrection, but that day was remarkable for the beginning of it.</p>
               <p n="3">3ly. There is a great Analogy between literal and ſpiritual <hi>Babylon,</hi> and the coming of Gods people out of that, and of the riſing of the Witneſſes and their deliverance from this. Now the people of God aroſe gradually out of literal <hi>Babylon.</hi> For 1. When the ſeventy years of their captivity were fulfilled,<note place="margin">Jer. 29.10.-15.</note> the Text tells us, that they muſt call upon the Lord, and go and pray to him and ſeek him; and ſearch for him with all their hearts, and then he would be found of them; then they ſhould do it, <hi>i. e.</hi> at the end of the 70 years. This then was their firſt motion in their Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; they muſt firſt of all riſe upon their knees.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Daniel</hi> did his part in this <hi>Calling, Praying, Seeking, Searching.</hi> And when did he do it? In the ſecond year of <hi>Darius</hi> the Son of <hi>Ahaſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> of the ſeed of the <hi>Medes,</hi> in which he was made King over the Realm of the <hi>Chaldeans, Dan.</hi> 9.1.</p>
               <p>This then was after the accompliſhment of the 70 years, becauſe the Kingdom of the <hi>Chaldeans</hi> was now at an end. For note what <hi>Jeremy</hi> ſaith, <hi>It ſhall come to paſs when</hi> 70 <hi>years are accompliſhed, that I will puniſh the King of</hi> Babylon; <hi>and that Nation, ſaith the Lord, for their iniquity, &amp;c. Jer.</hi> 25.12. It is apparent therefore that the 70 years were now ended, and that the time of the <hi>Jews</hi> deliverance was come; and yet (you ſee) after that very time did <hi>Daniel</hi> thus <hi>call, pray, ſeek, and ſearch.</hi> This (I ſay) is remarkable, as alſo, that after this time it was, that our Lord Jeſus Chriſt (the Angel of the Covenant) made interceſſion for the deliverance of his people, <hi>Zach.</hi> 1.12. Saith he, <hi>O Lord of hoſts, how long wilt thou not have mercy on</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>and on the Cities of</hi> Judah, <hi>againſt which thou haſt had indignation theſe threeſcore and ten years?</hi> God therefore ſeemed to delay a while, ſome may ſay, after the 70 years were
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:59095:9"/>ended, that our Lord Jeſus ſaith, <hi>How long,</hi> when the years were expired. Yea, but God did not delay one moment, <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.3. for the Jews Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection was now begun, for they were upon their knees, and Chriſt was interceding for them and in them. The Spirit of Life from God acted this way in them in their firſt motion; their riſing was ſomewhat like as when a man riſeth out of his bed, and falls down upon his knees by his Bed-ſide and prayeth. If any man now ſhould enquire and ſay, is ſuch a man riſen? it might truly be affirmed that he is ſo, though he be down upon his knees at preſent.<note place="margin">Iſa. 26.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>9.</note> It was propheſyed of the coming of the <hi>Jews</hi> out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> that their dew ſhould be as the dew of the herbs, and that the earth ſhould caſt forth her dead: Their Reſurrection out of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon</hi> ſhould be like the Reſurrection of Herbs in Spring, which ariſe out of the earth by degrees.</p>
               <p>And alſo when they did come out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> they came not out all at once, but at ſeveral times; ſome of them in the firſt year of King <hi>Cyrus,</hi> upon the Proclamation which he made, <hi>Ezr.</hi> 1. Others in the Reign of <hi>Artaxerxes,</hi> came out with <hi>Ezra</hi> the Scribe,<note place="margin">Neh. 2. &amp; 7.7.— which was 13 years after <hi>Ezra</hi>'s coming forth. <hi>Neh.</hi> 2.1. with <hi>Ezr.</hi> 7.7, 8.</note> 
                  <hi>Ezr.</hi> 7.1.—Others with <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemiah,</hi> in whoſe days alſo the bondage was not quite ended, <hi>Neh.</hi> 9.36, 37. So that it was upon that account alſo a kind of gradual Reſurrection or coming forth.</p>
               <p>It is true, there was liberty of returning granted by Proclamation in the firſt year of King <hi>Cyrus,</hi> but there fell in certain impediments that hindred both the ſpeedy progreſs of their coming forth, and alſo of their carrying on of Religion when they were come unto <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> for fear was upon them, <hi>Ezr.</hi> 3.3. and much oppoſition they met with for ſome years; for the people of the Land weakned the hands of the people of <hi>Judah,</hi> and troubled them in building, and hired Councellors againſt them, to fruſtrate their purpoſe all the days of <hi>Cyrus</hi> King of <hi>Perſia,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezr. 4th 5th, &amp; 6th Chapters.</note> unto the days of <hi>Darius</hi> the King thereof. They had ſtill very many Adverſaries.</p>
               <p>For Military Occaſions withdrew <hi>Cyrus,</hi> who left the Government to his Son <hi>Cambyſes,</hi> who proved an Enemy to the <hi>Jews,</hi> and to the build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Temple: He did not ſecond his Farthers Proclamation of Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but rather hid it in the Houſe of the Rolls, inſomuch, that it was at laſt quite forgotten, as you may ſee <hi>Ezr.</hi> 5.13. with 17. and <hi>chap.</hi> 6.1, 2. Note therefore what is ſaid, <hi>Dan.</hi> 10.1—<hi>In the third year of</hi> Cyrus <hi>King of</hi> Perſia, <hi>a thing was revealed unto</hi> Daniel, <hi>and the thing was true, but the time appointed was long—In thoſe days I</hi> Daniel <hi>was mourning three full weeks, I ate no pleaſant bread, neither came Fleſh or Wine into my mouth, &amp;c.</hi> It ſeems he underſtood of the oppoſitions which were made by <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byſes</hi> and his Emiſſaries againſt the work of God at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> even in the third year of King <hi>Cyrus,</hi> who gave the <hi>Jews</hi> their liberty in his firſt year.<note place="margin">Ezr. 4.</note> And upon this occaſion <hi>Daniel</hi> humbleth himſelf greatly, and waiteth to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:59095:10"/>know the mind of God, and what he purpoſed to do with his people: And our Lord Jeſus Chriſt appeared to him, and ſhewed him a great Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which aſtoniſhed him very much, and made him to fall down upon his face, and he was caſt into a deep ſleep, his face being towards the ground.</p>
               <p>And now behold, an Hand touched him which ſet him upon his knees, and upon the palms of his hands; afterward Chriſt ſaid unto him, <hi>Stand upright, for unt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thee am I ſent;</hi> and when he had ſpoken this word, <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> ſtood trembling. Chriſt could have ſet him upright upon his feet at once, but I have ſometimes thought whether our Lord Jeſus did not here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſhew unto <hi>Daniel,</hi> the gradual manner of the <hi>Je<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urrection out of <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bylon;</hi> for
<list>
                     <item>1. They did lye in <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>bylon</hi> as it were in a deep ſleep on their faces, as <hi>Iſalah</hi> propheſying of their coming out of Captivity, ſaith, <hi>Awake and ſing ye that dwell in the duſt.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Iſa. 26.19.</note>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. They ariſe but in a gradual manner, <hi>viz.</hi> upon their knees (as it were) and the palms of their hands.</item>
                     <item>3. They ſtand upright, but trembling; and therefore as if the Lord Jeſus ſhould bid <hi>Daniel</hi> not to be ſo much dejected, the people of God, for whom he was thus ſolicitous, ſhould ſtand upright in good time.</item>
                  </list> This (I have thought) is the intendment of Chriſt in this Viſion, and of what befell the Prophet under it; ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eing it is likely that Jeſus Chriſt would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct him by the Viſion and the Effects of it, concerning that buſineſs which lay moſt upon his Heart. Now to come to our purpoſe.</p>
               <p>Even thus the Witneſſes are dead aſleep in the duſt. 2. The Spirit of Life from God entreth into them, and they riſe firſt on their knees and palms of their Hands, and there they ſtick a while, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> they ſtand up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right but trembling, and then they begin to gather ſtrength by little and little, till at laſt their en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mies begin to ſtand trembling, and are afraid to look upon him, as we ſhall bear, <hi>ver.</hi> 12.</p>
               <p>Thus the Reſurrection here will be gradual, and (which is more) not be the buſineſs of a few days, though in my Text it is comprehended in a very few words.</p>
               <p>You know what vaſt Hiſtories are contained in the ſecond and ſeventh Chapters of <hi>Daniel,</hi> and in other alſo of his Viſions, which are but ſhort and brief in the Reading. And thus it is with very many Hiſtories in the Scriptures which are expreſſed with very great brevity. That which the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of Antichriſt,<note place="margin">2 Theſſ. 2.</note> and of what did then hinder his viſible appearance, and what he ſpeaks of his Wickedneſs, Revelation, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, Deſtruction, containeth many Centuries of years above a thouſand, and is the ſum of moſt that is contained in the Book of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations,</hi> from the ſixth Chapter to the End; In which Book how are large Stories contained in a very ſmall compaſs? The large Hiſtory of the ten Perſecutions lyeth in a narrow Room in the ſixth Chapter; the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:59095:10"/>and power of the <hi>Turk,</hi> and how he hath been a Scourge to the Antichriſtian World, lyeth within the one half of the ninth Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For it is in this Book, as in a ſmall Map of the vaſt World, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in very great Countreys are deſcribed in as narrow a compaſs as the breadth of your hand: And in the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ale of miles which you ſee in the bottom of the Map, the miles ſeem to be very ſhort, but he that tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velleth them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hall find them very long. And therefore I conceive we are much miſtaken, when we think that the entring of the Spirit of life into the Witneſſes, and their ſtanding upon their feet, and their aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a Cloud, are matters that fall out ſuddenly, and that follow cloſe one upon the heels of another. The ſlaying and riſing of the Witneſſes is a great part of that Story which is contained under the ſixth Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, which ſoundeth ſeveral hundreds of years, and yet you ſee not many things expreſſed during the time of its ſounding.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, That the riſing of the Witneſſes will be <hi>gradual,</hi> is apparent by the <hi>gradual</hi> fall of the Beaſt; for they cannot riſe faſter than he falls, like as in two Well-buckets, one cannot aſcend faſter than the other doth deſcend.</p>
               <p>Autichriſt, you know, hath been long aſcending to his height, and his Vertical point is at the time of the ſlaying of the Witneſſes, after which he will riſe no higher, but begin to deſcend, yet ſo as that it will not be preſently diſcerned, no more than the declining of the Sun is forthwith obſervable after his height in Summer; there is a Solſtice, or a ſtay or ſtand (as it were) of the Sun for a time after the longeſt day, before the declenſion thereof is viſible: For even thus it is with the Kingdom of the Beaſt after the riſing of the Witneſſes: And when that Kingdom of his doth decline viſibly, it will not fall ſuddenly, but God will firſt begin with a tenth part thereof, <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. as a pledge of the ruine of the whole City under the ſeventh Trumpet, which will ſound preſently upon the back of the fall of the ſaid tenth part. But the deſcending of the Beaſt to his Center, <hi>i. e.</hi> till he be caſt into the Lake that burneth with fire and Brimſtone, will take up many years, during which time the Church will ſtill be aſcending. And therefore we muſt not think that when the Witneſſes begin to ariſe, they will preſently (no nor in a few years neither) riſe up to their heighth; for they muſt aſcend as Antichriſt deſcendeth, and that is, <hi>gradually.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And by this we may collect, that it is a miſtake in ſuch as think, that when the Witneſſes begin to ariſe we ſhall have Halcyon dayes, in which the Saints ſhall begin to ride as it were in Triumph, and ſee ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row no more. For ſurely their life from the dead will not preſently become the death of the Beaſt; only, after a while, when he perceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:59095:11"/>that the Cauſe of Chriſt is in a riſing way, he will be ſorely af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted, as here <hi>verſ.</hi> 12. But great troubles will follow this Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection after a ſhort time; for the tenth part of the City (<hi>i. e.</hi> of the Beaſts Dominion) will not fall eaſily, as the walls of <hi>Jericho</hi> did, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſtriking of a ſtroak; there will be ſomewhat to do in the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Vengeance of Gods Witneſſes, which will ſhake the power of the Beaſt ſo far, that he ſhall loſe the tithe of his Dominion. There will be nothing but woful ſtirs and ſhakings, till it be come to <hi>Arma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geddon.</hi> For when the Beaſt perceives himſelf falling, who hath ſtood, and that ſtrongly, theſe many hundreds of years, he will rage like the Angel of the bottomleſs Pit,<note place="margin">Quoniam ad ſepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum clan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorem prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipatus Chriſti maximè eminet, ad ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus praecipu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us furor to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e nationis reſervatus eſt. <hi>Joh. Bright.</hi> in locum.</note> ſo that Hell it ſelf will be moved, and break looſe to help him.</p>
               <p>You know what is ſaid here after the ſounding of the Seventh Trumpet, <hi>The Nations were angry,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Chriſts Kingdom will begin to ſhine forth at the ſounding of the ſeventh Trumpet, and therefore the ſpecial rage of the Pontifician Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is reſerved unto that time. And if it be thus under the Seventh Trumpet which allarums the Beaſt more eſpecially, how will it be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſixth Trumpet, which is the ſaddeſt of all the Trumpets to the Church and People of God? And what a fearfull <hi>Farewell</hi> will it have? For it will not ceaſe ſounding preſently after the riſing of the Witneſſes, ſeeing there is an aſcending time to follow, and a great Earthquake at the heels thereof, which will make ſad work, and after that, <hi>The third Woe cometh quickly.</hi> Theſe things then will not be done upon a ſudden, nor without further tryals to the Church of God. For the Worſhips and Superſtitions of Antichriſt are woven (almoſt) into every thing throughout <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> the unravelling whereof will ſhake that part of the World where theſe things are ſo twiſted and interwoven, and ſo have been theſe hundreds of years. And therefore we muſt take heed that we do not judge of the riſing of the Witneſſes by the times that ſucceed it, but by that Reſurrection Spirit which (after a while) will appear in the Witneſſes of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>I ſhall conclude with a Conſectary flowing from what hath been ſpoken of the gradual riſing, and it will ſerve alſo in way of anſwer to the queſtion in hand; and it is this, <hi>viz.</hi> That ſeeing there is ſuch a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual motion, the firſt beginnings of the Reſurrection will not (in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability) be ſo perceivable. How imperceptible were the firſt moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Antichriſt?<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>The Myſtery of Iniquity</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>doth work al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready;</hi> and yet how few diſcerned him in the dayes of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> which was ſome hundreds of years after the Apoſtle thus wrote, and when alſo that which did let his more publick appearing and acting, was quite taken out of the way?</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:59095:11"/>
               <p>I ſuppoſe, they have been very few who at the opening of the Seals, and at the beginning of the ſounding of every Trumpet hitherto, could ſay, Now ſuch a Seal is opened; and heark, how ſuch or ſuch a Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet doth now begin to ſound.</p>
               <p>Beginnings are many times very ſmall and obſcure, as it is with Rivers which ariſe from little Fountains, and yet at laſt grow to be very deep. Perhaps alſo there may be in ſome an aptneſs to expect the accompliſhment of ſuch or ſuch a paſſage in the <hi>Revelati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ns,</hi> in ſuch a way as they have fore-fancyed, and then when the fulfilling of them is very different from their pre-conceptions, they may be ready to queſtion it. In our eager purſuits after accompliſhments, it may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen ſometimes that we may leave them behind us, and yet think that they are before us. A little waiting therefore will ſet our Judgments right as to the queſtion in hand, and give you a ſurer Anſwer than I ſhall undertake to do.</p>
               <p>One thing more; you have heard how the Death and Reſurrection of the Witneſſes do in many things anſwer to the Death and Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of Chriſt, though in ſome things again they differ: But if their Reſurrections correſpond in any thing, I am prone to think it is in their firſt beginnings: Let us conſider this a little, and finiſh the preſent diſcourſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. When Chriſt aroſe it was dark, and for ought I know to the contrary, it might be near Midnight.<note place="margin">Joh. 20.1.</note> When <hi>Mary Magdalene</hi> came to the Sepulchre, it was yet dark, and Chriſt was then riſen I know not how long before. And when ſhe ſaw Chriſt afterwards at the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre, ſhe neither knew him, nor that he was riſen, but miſtook him, thinking he had been the Gardiner; And when ſhe knew him, ſhe went and told them that had been with him, and found them mourning and weeping, who therefore little imagined that Chriſt was riſen.<note place="margin">Mark 16.10, 11.</note> And when theſe heard what ſhe ſaid, they believed it not; and when the two Diſciples told them the ſame, they did not believe them;<note place="margin">Mark 16.13.</note> for as yet they knew not the Scripture, that he muſt riſe again from the dead. And when he appeared afterward to the Eleven as they ſate at meat,<note place="margin">Joh. 20.9.</note> he upbraided them with their unbelief and hardneſs of heart,<note place="margin">Mark 16.14.</note> becauſe they believed not them that had been with him after he was riſen. And ſo too he upbraided the two Diſciples that went with him to <hi>Emmaus.</hi> And when he appeared to the Ten, <hi>Thomas</hi> (who was then abſent from them) would not believe that Chriſt was riſen; yea,<note place="margin">Luk. 24.37</note> and at his firſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing to them, they thought they had ſeen a Spirit, (which is more;) when the Diſciples went into <hi>Galilee</hi> into a Mountain where Chriſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared (which I conceive to be the time ſpoken of by the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">Matth. 28.17.</note> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.6.) it is ſaid, <hi>They worſhipped him, but ſome doubted.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:59095:12"/>
               <p>By all this you ſee, how difficultly the Reſurrection of Chriſt was believed. Even thus it may be when He riſeth in his Witneſſes, whoſe reſurrection doth (in many things as well as his death) allude to that of Chriſt's.</p>
               <p>The Witneſſes then (like Chriſt) may be up, and few know it, or believe it; that, as it is ſaid of the report of them who brought the firſt tidings of Chriſts reſurrection to his Diſciples, <hi>Their words ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>emed to them as idle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ales,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 24.11</note> 
                  <hi>and they believed them not:</hi> Even ſo it may happen at the reſurrection of the Witneſſes, who do not only aſcend, but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps alſo riſe in a cloud, as many times the Sun doth, inſomuch that ſome lye a bed till ſeven or eight of the Clock in the Spring in a cloudy Morning, and think not that the Sun is riſen.</p>
               <p>Now then, lay all the precedent paſſages together, and pray for light and help from the Spirit, and ſee what it doth amount unto. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever wait for a while lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ger, and time will prove a ſure Interpreter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>REV. XI. 12.</hi>
                     </bibl> And they heard a great Voice from Heaven, ſaying unto them, Come up hither; And they aſcended up to Heaven in a Cloud, and their Enemies beheld them.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>IN the former Verſe we find the Witneſſes upon their feet, in this we find them upon the wing. In the words you may obſerve,
<list>
                     <item>1. A Call given them, and it is by a <hi>Voice.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. It is a <hi>great</hi> Call, for it is a <hi>great Voice.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. From whence it cometh, <hi>from Heaven.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. The Witneſſes hearing it, <hi>They heard a great voice.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>5. What it ſaith, viz. <hi>Come up hither.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list> I ſhall only paraphraſe upon the verſe, and conclude with application.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And they heard a great Voice from Heaven.</hi>] <hi>Heaven</hi> is put for the Church here upon Earth. For as the Church is diſtinguiſhed from her ſeed; Chap. 12.17. So here, from her Witneſſes. The meaning therefore is, There comes a voice out of the Church to the Churches and Miniſters, to riſe up yet higher and nearer Heaven. For the Spirit ſpeaketh in the Churches to the Churches, as you may ſee in the ſecond and third <hi>Chapters</hi> of this Book of the <hi>Revelations.</hi> This I take to be the meaning of the words.
<list>
                     <item>1. It ſeems to be ſet here in oppoſition to the Beaſt, who is ſaid to aſcend out of the bottomleſs pit, <hi>ver.</hi> 7. The Beaſt lives in Hell upon Earth, the Saints in Heaven.</item>
                     <item>2. It ſtands alſo in oppoſition to the former condition
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:59095:12"/>that the Witneſſes were in, who but now lay dead (as it were) upon the earth, and now, behold, they are called up to Heaven.</item>
                     <item>3. This Heaven is the ſame that is mentioned <hi>ver.</hi> 19. but that is the Church of God, and therefore ſo is this.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Now the voice that calls to them from this Heaven, is a great Voice, declaring a loud call. Here then is a Commiſſion and Warrant given them to propheſie again, and to follow their former employment, and not in the leaſt to be diſcouraged, for their Call is very clear, diſtinct, and audible, it being a <hi>great voice.</hi> And ſome do conceive, that this Call comes from men in publick place; and I ſhould be glad it might prove ſo; but I much doubt of it, upon theſe grounds.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe it is ſaid, That when they aſcended up to Heaven in a cloud, their Enemies beheld them. Now theſe enemies are thoſe who lately ſlew them, and therefore were men of Place and Power. And ſtill they are the men they were, as very Enemies at the Reſurrection and Aſcenſion of the Witneſſes, as when they ſlew them; Therefore ſurely theſe could not call them; They who beheld them as Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies when they aſcended up to Heaven, would never call them up to Heaven.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is ſaid in the following words, That in <hi>the ſame hour there was a great Earthquake, and the tenth part of the City fell, and in the Earthquake were ſlain of men ſeven thouſand.</hi> Theſe are the enemies ſpoken of in my Text, as I ſhall further ſhew you when I come to <hi>ver.</hi> 13. So that this call here comes not from men in publick place, they are enemies (you ſee) after the Reſurrection, and at the Aſcenſion of the Witneſſes; And the Voice here comes from Heaven, which is no place for the enemies of the Witneſſes.</p>
               <p>This Voice then comes from the Spirit of God in the Churches, work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an inward powerful inſtinct and impreſſion in theſe Witneſſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>They heard a great Voice.</hi>] It is not ſaid, that others heard it. It is ſomewhat like the voice which <hi>Pau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> heard from Heaven,<note place="margin">Act. 22.5.</note> when he was near unto <hi>Damaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>;</hi> They that were with him ſaw the light that ſhined about him, but they heard not the voice of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im that ſpake to him: That is, They did not hear it diſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tly; for <hi>the men that journeyed with him ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>od ſpeechleſs, hearing a Voice,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 9.7.</note> 
                  <hi>but ſeeing no man.</hi> It was a Voice, and a great, clear, diſtinct voice, but in <hi>Paul</hi>'s ears only, not in theirs. So here, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But what is the ſubject matter of this call? <hi>Come up hither;</hi>] Not l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g ago, there was a great voice, or vote, from He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> againſt theſe Witneſſes; and now there is a voice from Heaven to them, and fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>em; The firſt was from the Beaſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending out of the Bottomleſs p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, this is from the Spirit ſpeaking from Heaven to them; The firſt cryed, <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> with them:</hi> This from Heaven
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:59095:13"/>cries, Up with them; <hi>Come up hither;</hi> The firſt laid them as it were upon the Earth in the ſtreets; This calls them up to Heaven.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> But what ſhall they do there? <hi>Anſw.</hi> Wherefore, as if the voice ſhould ſay, Here is more work for you, the Church is riſing higher than it was; It is nearer Heaven, more pure and refined, more ſet upon Separation, more elevated above the world, and preparing for more glorious times approaching under the ſeventh Trumpet; and therefore, <hi>Come up hither;</hi> which intimateth, that formerly they preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, lived, and converſed at a lower rate than now they muſt, and are here called to do; For the Churches are riſen, and all things in the Churches are higher, and got up nearer unto Heaven, and the Saints muſt now live far above their former ſelves; Wherefore, abide no long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er where you are, but <hi>Come up hither.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in this Call, there is a motion implyed, <hi>Come,</hi> which hath a term from which.
<list>
                     <item>1. The <hi>Earth,</hi> or a lower condition of living be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, when the Witneſſes ſavoured too much of the Earth, and when their Spirits lay proſtrate during the time of their ſlaughter; For as the death of the Witneſſes was in a ſpecial manner Spiritual, their ſpirits being low and dead, ſo now their Spirits are raiſed up higher.</item>
                     <item>2. They move and riſe up from Antichriſt and his Pollutions, and all his earthly and helliſh waies of Worſhip, Mixtures, and baſe converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</item>
                     <item>3. From that Bondage and ſervitude which the Witneſſes were lately in unto the Wills of men, before their Reſurrection; ſo that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time after their Reſurrection there will be a very great change in the Churches of Chriſt, as to purity of Doctrine and Worſhip, and Holineſs of walking, and Goſpel-liberty, far beyond what was before. Thus you ſee their Call cleared.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. I come now to their Obedience to this Call, or great Voice from Heaven.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And they aſcended up to Heaven in a cloud, and their Enemies beheld them.</hi>] In which words, there are three things conſiderable.
<list>
                     <item>1. Their Aſcent to <hi>Heaven.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. In what manner, <hi>in a Cloud.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. Who ſaw them thus aſcending; <hi>their Enemies beheld them.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>They aſcended up to Heaven.</hi> The great Voice is accompanied with great Power, that the thing commanded is ſoon accompliſhed. They willingly and readily attend the Call, declaring that their hearts were wholly in it. <hi>Come up hither;</hi> Lo, we come; and muſt we yet be more ſeparate from ſin and ſinners, as to communion with them, and from Antichriſtian pollutions, and from the world? We deſire nothing more. And muſt we be more conform to Rule, in Church, in Family, and in all our Relations, Conditions, and Converſations in this world? We chearfully attend this call from Heaven. They are not therefore
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:59095:13"/>paſſive in aſcending, as men that are haled up from the Earth ſo as if their feet ſtuck in the mire, and as <hi>Jeremy</hi>'s body was drawn up by cords out of the Dungeon; but they ſeem to leap up Heaven-ward. Only this is not done preſently after their Reſurrection, but like unto Chriſt's Aſcenſion to Heaven in a cloud, ſome good ſpace of time after his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For the Manner; <hi>They aſcended in a cloud;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 1.9.</note> wherein there is an alluſion unto the manner of Chriſt's Aſcenſion into Heaven. But what doth this Cloud here ſignifie?</p>
               <p n="1">1. It noteth their aſcending in a Degree of glory. <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.30. There is now a Spirit of glory reſting upon them. As it was with Chriſt when he roſe from the dead, he layd aſide for ever his ſtate of Humiliation: So do theſe Witneſſes; they ſhall now propheſie in ſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloath no more, they ſhall henceforth be cloathed with a cloud of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. And as Chriſt's Reſurrection was the firſt degree of his Exaltati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and his Aſcenſion the ſecond; even ſo it is here with his Witneſſes; For this is the ſecond degree of their Exaltation, the third will be when they ſhall dye and enter into glory; and the laſt, when they ſhall come with Chriſt to judge the world.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Here is alſo Power denoted in this <hi>cloud,</hi> as you may ſee from the former Text, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.30. For the Witneſſes were ſlain in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour, but they ſhall be raiſed (eſpecially aſcend) in glory; ſlain in weakneſs, but raiſed and aſcend in power, as it is alſo ſaid of Chriſt,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 13.4.</note> that he was crucified through <hi>weakneſs,</hi> but he liveth by the <hi>power</hi> of God.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Hereby is ſignified their Protection and ſafe paſſage and proceedings in the way of further Reformation, like as the Cloud in the Wilderneſs was a defence upon <hi>Iſrael</hi> when they were come up out of <hi>Egypt;</hi> for thus now, upon all the glory there ſhall be a Defence. The caſe alſo is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what like as when the <hi>Egyptians</hi> purſued the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> into the Red Sea, at what time the pillar of cloud removed from before the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> and ſtood between them and the <hi>Egyptians;</hi> For thus, here is a cloud of Protection between the aſcending Witneſſes and their Enemies.</p>
               <p n="4">4. This cloud ſignifieth the Obſcurity of this aſcenſion, as to their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies who ſtand here looking on them. For clouds are ſometimes put for darkneſs. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 97.2. And as it is ſaid of the Pillar of cloud that ſtood between the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> and the <hi>Egyptians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 14.20.</note> 
                  <hi>It was a cloud</hi> and darkneſs to the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> but it gave light by night unto the <hi>Iſraelites:</hi> Even ſo, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And therefore though there are many lookers on here to ſee the aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Witneſſes, yet they do not underſtand what God is about to do in this ſo glorious a diſpenſation, but are ready to ſay as <hi>Samballat,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Neh. 4.2.</note> 
                  <hi>What do theſe feeble Jews? Will they fortify themſelves? Will they ſacrifice? Will they make
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:59095:14"/>an end in a day? will they revive the ſtones out of the heaps of the rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſh which are burnt?</hi> Why? What is that which blindeth their eyes? It is their malice, envy and hatred; for you ſee they are ſtill called <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,</hi> even when the Witneſſes aſcend. God hath hardened their hearts, and blinded their eyes, and given them up to a reprobate ſence, and to the power of prevailing enmity. Beſides which, They look upon there Aſcenders as clouded with reproaches and calumnies, which hath ſtill been the Lot of the Saints in all times of Reformation. So that, neither the Reſarrection, nor Aſcenſion have altered them, nor opened their eyes in the leaſt. Thus much for the Manner of the Witneſſes Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Here follows the Spectators of this Aſcenſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And their Enemies beheld them.</hi>] There is a fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r-fold Beholding of them by their Enemies.
<list>
                     <item>1. They beheld them <hi>propheſying,</hi> and that was with Torment, <hi>ver.</hi> 10.</item>
                     <item>2. They beheld them <hi>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ain,</hi> and this was with joy, for they rejoiced over them, and made merry, and ſent gifts one to another.</item>
                     <item>3. They beheld them <hi>riſen,</hi> and that was with fear, <hi>ver.</hi> 11.</item>
                     <item>4. They here behold them <hi>aſcending,</hi> and that is with grief and Indignation.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>But that which is here remarkable is, 1. The Progreſs which the Witneſſes make in their Reformation after their ſlaughter is finiſhed; for,
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>The Spirit of Life from God enter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>th into them.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>They ſtand upon their feet.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. <hi>They aſcend up to Heaven.</hi> For ſurely ſuch a progreſſion there will be.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. It is obſervable, that as the Witneſſes are called to this Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by a great Voice from Heaven, ſo a great power attends the work, inſomuch that their Enemies cannot hinder it by any means, though the perſons and their work are very viſible to their eyes; for they ſee both them and it with fear, grief, and Indignation, like as <hi>Tobiah, Sanballat, Goſhem,</hi> and the reſt of their companions, beheld the repairing the Wall of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> but could not put a ſtop to it: For juſt ſo it is here with theſe Enemies. The caſe is ſomewhat like that which the Pſalmiſt mentioneth concerning the Kings of the Nations, who came up againſt <hi>Zion;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſ. 48.4, 5, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> ſaith he, <hi>Lo, the Kings were aſſembled, they paſſed by toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; they ſaw it, and ſo they marvelled, they were troubled and haſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away; fear took hold upon them there, and pain as of a Woman in Travel.</hi> They ſaw <hi>Zion,</hi> and were troubled, affrighted, and pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed greatly, and that was all that they could do. And like as the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, who guarded the Sepulchre of Chriſt, ſaw him as he aroſe, and feared,<note place="margin">Marth. 23.4.</note> and ſhook, and became like dead men, but were not able to lift up a weapon againſt him: Even ſo it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> here, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Whereas in the time of the ſlaughter, a Child of God could ſcarce ſtir, but theſe Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:59095:14"/>preſently beheld it, and not only ſo, but alſo oppoſed and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered it; but after their Reſurrection, eſpecially their Aſcenſion, they ſhall behold the Witneſſes, and do little or nothing more to ſpeak of.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It is remarkable, that the Enemies of the Witneſſes do ſtill retain their Enmity unto the laſt, even though they do moſt evidently behold that their ſlaying of the Witneſſes is come to nothing, but (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all endeavours to the contrary) they are up and upon their feet again, yea, and aſcending alſo, as reſolved upon a further Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; For yet ſtill you ſee that here they are called <hi>Enemies,</hi> even when the Witneſſes are upon the wing for Heaven. They are a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of Vipers, the ſeed of the Serpent, whoſe malice is implacable. And why are they ſuch <hi>Enemies?</hi> Not for any hurt that the Witneſſes and people of God have done them, for theſe would fain be quiet and live peaceably, for they oppoſe not Government here, but endeavour further to reform among themſelves. Their condition is much like that of <hi>David;</hi> ſaith he, <hi>They that render evil for good are mine Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, becauſe I follow the thing that good is.</hi> Oh what a dreadful account will theſe Enemies have, when neither the wonderful Providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of God, nor notable Diſappointments, nor Reformation, nor Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in Churches and Saints, can by any means turn them from their En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity and oppoſition even againſt God himſelf! And thus much for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of this 12th. <hi>verſe;</hi> Let me add a few Uſes, and conclude.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>USES.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. We are ſhewed, that when the Witneſſes are riſen, God calls them after a while to an higher pitch of Reformation: I ſay, <hi>After a while;</hi> For their Reſurrection (as you have heard) is gradual, and when they are arrived ſo far that they ſtand upon their feet, and have attained to ſome ſtrength and ſtability, then God calls them by a great Voice from Heaven to Come up higher, and to approach nearer unto Heaven. God doth not raiſe up his Witneſſes, that now they ſhould ſit down, and content themſelves to live as they did before; the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection is the firſt degree of Glory, and God doth now expect that they ſhould live above the world.</p>
                  <p>What the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.1. may well be applyed to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in hand; <hi>If ye be riſen with Chriſt, ſeek thoſe things which are above.</hi> Churches muſt now reform, and be riſing up nearer and nearer towards Heaven; and ſo it muſt be alſo with Families and Perſons. Eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially Miniſters, Churches and Church-members muſt be advancing forward, and preſſing after an higher point of holineſs and conformity to the Goſpel; for the Witneſs and teſtimony lyeth eſpecially among theſe;
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:59095:15"/>And God calls from Heaven to them with a loud voice to aſcend; Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if the Churches and Saints were at their ſet pirch, God would not ſay to them, as here he doth, <hi>Come up hither.</hi> It is not therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ough that they are ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on from the dead, and have the ſpirit of life in them, but they muſt alſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>and upon their feet; ſtand faſt, grow ſtrong, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> laſt aſcend <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ward. They muſt now grow and encrea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>,<note n="*" place="margin">1 King. 22.35.</note> as the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ame word in the Original is rendred both to <hi>aſcend</hi> and <hi>increaſe;</hi> they muſt be going and growing<note n="†" place="margin">2 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>am. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> as it is ſaid of <hi>David</hi> when he came to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. And doth God call from Heaven? take heed then that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> refu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e not him that ſpeaketh for how ſhall they eſcape who tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h awa; from him that ſpeaketh from Heaven?</p>
                  <p>As for publick and general Reformation, God calls aloud this day for it; but it is our duty to leave that unto our Superiours; As for our ſelves, we ſhall be left wholly without excuſe, if we take up our ſtand and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour not to aſcend yet higher. As touching others, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> not this Voice, nor will they hear it when it ſhall hereafter come to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> great Voice; for they are like the People who ſtood cloſe by Chriſt when there came a voice from Heaven,<note place="margin">Joh. 12.28.</note> ſaying unto him, <hi>I have both glo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>ed my Name, and will glorify it again;</hi> which when the ſtanders by heard, they ſaid, <hi>that it Thundered.</hi> It ſeemeth therefore that it was a very great voice, and yet the matter ſpoken was hidden from them. Others ſaid, <hi>An Angel ſpake unto him;</hi> how beit Chriſt tells them, That voice came for their ſakes, but (you ſee) they underſtood it not.</p>
                  <p>But let us hear what the Lord ſpeaketh; for we have this day a voice from Heaven, though the great Voice is not as yet come. Let us hear what is come, and though it be but a ſtill ſmall voice, yet God is in it, and therefore let us wrap our faces in our mantles, fear God, and obey his voice.</p>
                  <p>For ſurely God calls now for a more full Reformation in the Churches, and more exact walking according to Goſpel-pattern; and why ſhould we ſtay till the great voice cometh? When that cometh, the Witneſſes will hear, as the Text declareth, as much as to ſay, Till then they will not hear, at leaſt be ſo attentive. For thus God calls, and calls, and few will hear, that at laſt he is fain to call with a loud voice; In the mean while it is the ſin of ſuch who are thus dull of hearing. Do not therefore ſay as ſometimes the Jews did concerning the building of the Temple, <hi>The time is not yet come;</hi> ſo, the great voice hath not, as yet, ſpoken; but if there be any thing of a Reſurrection-ſpirit in us, let us live at an higher rate, and far above our ſlain ſelves. Surely, when the Witneſſes are riſen from the dead (whether it be done, or as yet to come) they will preach, and ſpeak, and pray, and partake of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and buy, and ſell, and converſe, at a Reſurrection-rate, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:59095:15"/>when once they begin to ſtand upon their feet, and to be warmed with the Spirit of life from <hi>God in them.</hi> And God will go on with a further Reformation before the 7th Trumpet ſoundeth; yea, you ſee that he calls for aſcending higher immediately before the coming of the Earthquake, ſaying, as ſometimes <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ſhua</hi> to the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Joſh. 3.5.</note> 
                     <hi>Sanctify your ſelves, for to morrow God will do wonders among you.</hi> Make haſt, get ye up with all ſpeed, and ſtand clear of the Earthquake.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. We are further informed, That when the Witneſſes are riſen, they ſhall not dye again, they are now beyond any more ſlaughters; And as it is ſaid of Chriſt in another kind, ſo it may be ſaid of his Witneſſes, <hi>Chriſt being raiſed from the dead,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 6.5.</note> 
                     <hi>dyeth no more.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And as there was Counſel in the former point of Information, ſo there is Comfort in this. The Teſtiomony of Jeſus after its Reſurrection ſhall live for ever, that as Chriſt ſaith of his own death and Reſurrection, his Teſtimony may ſpeak likewiſe, <hi>I am be that live<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h and was dead,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rev. 1.18.</note> 
                     <hi>and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, I am alive for evermore.</hi> The joy and mirth of the Beaſt at the ſlaughter of the Witneſſes could not keep them down from riſing again; nor ſhall their fears, and griefs, and wrath, and indignation at their Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on prevail to ſlay them a ſecond time. This is great mercy, and not a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle comfort.</p>
                  <p>When the <hi>Iſra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lites</hi> roſe up out of their boudage in <hi>Egypt,</hi> they roſe (as you have heard) by degrees, and were not compleatly riſen till they came up out of the Red Sea; and though all the power of <hi>Egypt</hi> purſued them to reduce them to their former ſervitude, and to ſlay them once again, they could not prevail, God would not ſuffer <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his hoſt to come near them, but he interpoſeth by the Pillar of cloud between them, as if he ſhould ſay, You ſhall as ſoon ſlay me as them; not an hair of their heads ſhall periſh. Yea, but ſhall not the Witneſſes meet with oppoſitions and exerciſes from the men of the world after their Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Yes, they may have many attempts made againſt them to deſtroy them, for even to their very Aſcenſion (as you ſee here in the Text) they have their Enemies, for <hi>their Enemies behold them;</hi> They behold them both riſing and aſcending, they have ſtill an eye upon them.</p>
                  <p>The Enmity therefore doth not ceaſe at the Reſurrection or Aſcenſion, but rather increaſe upon that very account; for the Witneſſes riſe, and (at laſt) aſcend, and their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>emies cannot help it, they can behold them, as the Text ſhe weth us, and that is all that is here ſpoken of them. The Witneſſes ſhall meet with enm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>y enough, but with no more ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, attempts perhaps that way, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſtill f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſtraueous. We muſt not therefore judge of the Reſurrection <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Aſcenſion of the Witneſſes by the enmity and affronts which they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ay meet with, for what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> can be expected from <hi>Enemies?</hi> The priviledge of the ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>en Witneſſes is,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:59095:16"/>not that they ſhall ſuffer no more, but that they ſhall be ſlain no more.<note n="*" place="margin">Joh. 12.10.</note> When <hi>Lazarus</hi> was riſen from the dead, the chief Prieſts conſulted to take away his life, but they could not do it; will any therefore ſay, that <hi>Lazarus</hi> was not riſen from the dead, becauſe the Hierarchy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted to kill him? No; Do not therefore miſgive as to the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Witneſſes, upon every petty or particular indignity that ſome one or more of them may meet with from their enemies. When the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were riſen up out of the Red Sea, they were gone no further than to <hi>Rephidim,</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Exod. 19 1, 2.</note> which was within three months, e're they met with an hoſt of <hi>Amalekites,</hi> who gave them a ſore aſſault, and when <hi>Moſes</hi> let down his hands, prevailed againſt them; but <hi>Iſrael</hi> had the day, and diſcomſited them, who were afterwards devoted to utter deſtruction for this their cruel and wicked attempt.<note n="*" place="margin">Exod. 19 4.</note> 
                     <hi>Iſrael</hi> was now born up on Eagles Wings, out of the reach of deſtroying dangers, and of fear of Reduction into Egyptian bondage; and now they paſs on ſtill from Journey to Journey in the Wilderneſs, and though at laſt they meet with <hi>Og</hi> and <hi>Sihon</hi> in the way, yet they ſubdue them, and never ſtop till they arrive in <hi>Canaan.</hi> Thus it will be with the Witneſſes after their Reſurrection.</p>
                  <p>The Churches and Saints will meet with ſome ſhakings after the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and Aſcenſion, becauſe there is a great Earthquake preſently to follow; <hi>ver.</hi> 13. After Chriſt's Aſcenſion, the Goſpel, its Preachers and Profeſſors had many encounters with their enemies; for preſently<note n="*" place="margin">Act. 4.26</note> 
                     <hi>The Kings of the Earth ſtood up, and the Rulers were gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againſt the Lord, and againſt his Chriſt;</hi> but in all the ſtory of the <hi>Acts</hi> of the Apoſtles, you find the Goſpel growing and getting ground by oppoſition, and they were but two, <hi>Stephen</hi> and <hi>James,</hi> who loſt their lives. And though we have an expectation of a great Earthquake, yet it is comfortable to conſider, that immediately before it cometh, a great Voice ſaith unto the Witneſſes, <hi>Come up hither,</hi> and that the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend up to Heaven in a cloud. It is a mercy, and will prove a means of the greater ſecurity, that they are got up nearer unto Heaven, and unto an higher degree of Holineſs, Purity of Doctrine, Worſhip, Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, and manner of living, before the ſtorm cometh. The ſafeſt living is above the Earth, in the Heaven of holineſs, when the Earth ſhall ſhake and reel to and fro like a drunken man; And this ſhall be the caſe of the Witneſſes aſcended.</p>
                  <p>You never find a Reformation in the Scriptures, but if there followed a ſhaking time, the People of God ſped well, or much the better for it.</p>
                  <p>When the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> put away their ſtrange Gods and <hi>Aſhteroth</hi> from among them,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 7.4—</note> and prepared their hearts unto the Lord, and ſerved him onely, and poured out water before him, and faſted, and confeſſed their
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:59095:16"/>ſins, preſently the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> are gathered together againſt them, and draw neer to battel; but the Lord thundered upon them and diſcomfit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them, and they are ſmitten before <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>When <hi>Jchoſaphat</hi> had reformed his Kingdom, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19. it came to paſs afterwards that the Inhabitants of <hi>Moah, Ammon</hi> and Mount <hi>Seir,</hi> came up to war againſt <hi>Judah,</hi> but God turned their ſwords againſt one another, and deſtroyed them without a ſtroke ſtruck by the men of <hi>Judah,</hi> 2 Chro. 20.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">2 Chro. 29.30, 31. 2 Chro. 30.</note> When <hi>Hezekiah</hi> had finiſhed an eminent Reformation in <hi>Judah, Sennacherib</hi> comes up againſt the land with a very formidable Army; but the Angel of the Lord ſlew therein an hundred fourſcore and five thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand in one night.</p>
                  <p>And in all theſe confuſions of the enemies of God and his People, after a Reformation wrought, it is obſervable, that God doth work wonders from Heaven, his People do little or nothing but pray and ſtand ſtill; And I am thinking whether God will not work wonderfully from Heaven by his own immediate hand when the great Earthquake cometh, ſoon after the Aſcenſion of the Witneſſes.</p>
                  <p>The Enemy cometh upon a very great diſadvantage to himſelf againſt the People of God, when once they are in an aſcending way of Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. It is great preſumption in theſe enemies here to ſlay the Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; to oppoſe them and oppreſs them in their ſackcloath is a cruel and accur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed thing; what then will God account it, if they ſhall dare to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign againſt them when cloathed with a Cloud? This is a very high degree of <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>omachy.</hi> For, as for the Dragon and the Beaſt, they will not be quiet till the ſeventh Vyal is poured out, and both are ſhut up in the bottomleſs Pit; yea, when the Devil is looſed out of priſon at the end of the thouſand years, the firſt thing he doth, is, he gathereth <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> together againſt the Camp of the Saints. He and his Inſtruments will never ceaſe their oppoſition, till they are thrown together into Hell, there to remain for ever. Wherefore, after the Reſurrection of the Witneſſes, the Saints may meet, and are like ſo to do, with many trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles to the pouring out of the laſt Vial, but yet they ſhall meet with no more ſlaughters. For what do we meet with as to theſe <hi>Enemies,</hi> after the riſing of the Witneſſes?
<list>
                        <item>1. It is ſaid of them, that <hi>great fear fell upon them.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. That, when the Witneſſes <hi>aſcended, they beheld them.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>3. When the Earthquake cometh, <hi>many fall, and the remnant is affrighted.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>4. When the ſeventh Trumpet ſoundeth, <hi>they are angry.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>5. When the fourth Vial is poured out, <hi>they blaſpheme.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>6. When the fifth, they <hi>gnaw their tongues and blaſpheme.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>7. When the ſixth, they <hi>gather themſelves toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the battle of the great day of God Almighty.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list> So that here is fear, anger, ſhewing of teeth, blaſpheming and gnawing of tongues, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:59095:17"/>great preparations to ſight, kill and conquer; and this is all that I find after the Reſurrection of the Witneſſes unto the laſt Vial, which will end in their everlaſting confuſion. Make therefore the Reſurrection ſure, and though there will be ſtirrs and ſtruglings, attempts and oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, and ſome particular ſufferings now and then, yet no great or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable hurt will be done unto the very laſt.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. If the Witneſſes ſhall thus riſe and afterward aſcend, then it will follow, that from thence forwards the Beaſt will not riſe higher, but be continually in the declining hand unto the very laſt; During which time will be made good in a pecial manner what is propheſied of him by the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 2.8.</note> The Lord ſhall conſume that <hi>wicke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> with the breath of his mouth. And this consi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ption ſhall more eminently begin with the fall of the tenth part of the City, and when the ſeventh Vial is poured out, he ſhall be deſtroyed with the brightneſs of Chriſt's coming.</p>
                  <p>He ſhall never thrive more after the ſlaughter of the Witneſſes, he ſhall never digeſt the ſhedding of their blood, which ſhall cry night and day to Heaven againſt him for vengeance. Let us but riſe and aſcend, let once a Reſurrection Spirit appear amongſt us, a Spirit of Faith, Love, Power and Zeal, a Spirit of Prayer, Praiſe, Reformation, holy walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and it will prove a Bleſſed Omen to us of the coming of Chriſt's King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and of the declenſion of the Beaſt's dominion. If we aſcend, he will of courſe deſced; for we and he cannot aſcend, nor deſcend to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, we are ſo diametrically oppoſire, that contrary fates do of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty attend us.</p>
                  <p>Now then, out of all that hath been ſaid, you may gather up theſe Conſequents of the Witneſſes Reſurrection.
<list>
                        <item>1. That as the Spirit of Life from God entreth into them, ſo now they will be more bold, active and zealous for God; only as the Reſurrection is gradual, ſo this Spirit of Life cometh on by degrees.</item>
                        <item>2. They attain, at laſt, to ſome ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, and begin to ſtand upon their feet, as being more fixed, ſtrengthned and reſolved.</item>
                        <item>3. When it is come thus far, grear fear falls upon them that ſee them, and their enemies begin now to be affrighted; As the Witneſſes grow ſtronger in faith, their enemies grow weaker with fear.</item>
                        <item>4. When thus they begin to gather ſtrength, and their enemies to grow more and more feeble, the Spirit of God gives the Witneſſes a loud call to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the opportunity, and to aſcend to an higher pitch of Reformation, raiſing them up above the earth and earthly things, and ſeparating them more from the world and the things of Antichriſt.</item>
                        <item>5. And now, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of ſackcloath, they are cloathed with a cloud, and a Spirit of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and glory reſteth on them.</item>
                        <item>6. They ſhall ſtill have enemies notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all this, and their enemies eyes ſhall be much upon them with vexation and anguiſh, but yet they ſhall not know how to help themſelves,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:59095:17"/>nor how to hinder this work of God, the external face whereof they ſhall ſee, but not the meaning of the diſpenſation, the Cloud interpoſing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them and that, ſo that they ſhall be blinded and hardened like <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raon</hi> and the <hi>Egyptian,</hi> they ſhall be under the power of a dedolent Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and ſtill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>ain their enmity.</item>
                        <item>7. This Aſcenſion of the Witneſſes im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately foreruns the Earthquake, giving hopes of greater ſecurity to the Witneſſes in ſuch a day of dreadful concuſſion, when God will make ſome notable diſtinction between them and their enemies.</item>
                     </list> If therefore you ſhould live to ſee the Witneſſes upon their feet, expect after a while to ſee them upon the wing; and if you ſee them aſcending, expect ere long that Earthquake, whereof I ſhall ſpeak in the next diſcourſe, which will cauſe great ruines, and effect ſtrange alterations. When the Witneſſes begin to aſcend, the great City will begin to deſcend, and pay the rithe of it ſelf to divine Vengeance for its late blood-guiltineſs, of which more upon the next Verſe. So much for this.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>VERSE 13.</hi>
                     </bibl> And the ſame hour there was a great Earthquake, and the tenth part of the City fell, and in the Earthquake were ſlain of men ſeven thouſand; and the remnant were affrighted, and gave glory to the God of Heaven.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>WE are now come to the Concluſion of the ſixth Trumpet, which endeth with an Earthquake; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Earthquake is deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed,
<list>
                     <item>1. By its Greatneſs, for it is ſaid to be <hi>a great Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. By the time when it happened, <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. By the effects or conſequents of it;</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. That <hi>the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>th, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> of the City fell.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. That therein <hi>were ſlain of men ſeven thouſand.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. That <hi>the remnant were affright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. That they <hi>gave glory to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> God of He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                              <desc>••••</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall handle the words as I did the former <hi>verſe,</hi> by way of Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſe, or E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d the ſame hour.</hi>] Not th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>hour of their Reſurrection: the <hi>Earthquake</hi> here is reſerved for the W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſſes. Aſce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>on, after which it haſteth, coming in <hi>the ſam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly take<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, but Metaphorically, <hi>i. e.</hi> Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> For it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>den and anexpected ſucceſſion of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the Witneſſes. Let but theſe once <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>y <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> falls a ſhaking; for (<note n="*" place="margin">Vindicta divina de teſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micis. <hi>Joh. Piſc.</hi> in h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum.</note> as <hi>Piſcat.</hi> well <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>) this in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ce of God upon the enemies of the Witneſſes; they were now gazing up to Heaven to ſee the Witneſſes
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:59095:18"/>aſcending, and, before they are aware, they are ſurprized with a grea Earthquake from under them. For this <hi>verſe</hi> is connected with the Aſcenſion of the Witneſſes by the Copulative <hi>And,</hi> ſhewing us, that it belongeth to the ſame ſtory, and followeth cloſe upon the Aſcenſion. The Enemies were ſtaring upon the Aſcenders, and upon a ſudden the Earth ſhaketh under them, and turns their eyes upon another object. God threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to throw them down to Hell, whileſt his Witneſſes are aſcending up to Heaven.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And the ſame hour there was an Earthquake.</hi>] There are two ſorts of Earthquakes in the Scriptures.
<list>
                     <item>1. Such as are Natural, as when the earth ſhaketh through collection of Wind and Vapours in the bowels thereof, and which want vent. Such an Earthquake there was in the dayes of King <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Zach. 14.5.</note> and ſuch before the deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem, Luk.</hi> 21.11.</item>
                     <item>2. There are figurative and metaphorical Earthquakes in the Scripture, as when ſome notable diſpenſation of God reſembleth an Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake; and ſuch is this here in the Text.</item>
                  </list> And this, in Scripture, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies ſome notable change,<note place="margin">Hebr. 12.26, 27.</note> as when God ſaith, <hi>Yet once more I ſhake not the Earth only, but alſo Heaven;</hi> This (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>ſignifieth the removing of thoſe things that are ſhaken.</hi> And when God ſaith, He <hi>will ſhake the Heavens and the Earth,</hi> mark what a change followeth: <hi>And I will over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the throne of Kingdoms, and I will deſtroy the ſtrength of the Kingdoms of the Heathen, and I will overthrow the Chariots and thoſe that ride in them, and the horſes and their riders ſhall come down, every one by the ſword of his brother. Hag.</hi> 2.21, 22. See alſo <hi>Iſa.</hi> 13.13. And theſe Metapho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical and figurative Eathquakes are ſometimes accompanied with or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaged by literal ones, as in that place of <hi>Luke</hi> forementioned. And that formidable Earthquake in the dayes of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah</hi> happened about the time that <hi>Jehu</hi>'s fourth Generation was expiring, after which followed frequent and fearful changes unto the very Captivity of the ten Tribes. Again; When God brought his people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> this was a perio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dical time, and there was now a very great change coming upon the World, and the Church therein, not the like thereunto (excepting in the time of the Deluge) from the foundation of the World. <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and the <hi>Egyptians</hi> were now to be deſtroyed in the Red Sea, and the Church to paſs into <hi>Canaan,</hi> and there to ſettle; And God ſignified this great change by an Earthquake properly and literally ſo called. <hi>O God</hi> (ſaith the Pſalmiſt) <hi>when thou wenteſt forth before thy people, when thou didſt march thorow the wilderneſs, the earth ſhook, the Heavens alſo dropped at the preſince of God, even Sinai it ſelf was moved at the preſence of God, the God of Iſrael.</hi> Pſ. 68.7, 8. See alſo, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 77.15, 16. to the end. The Earthquake therefore in my text ſignifies ſome great and emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent change brought in with ſhaking and affrighting Judgments, common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:59095:18"/>for the deſtruction of Gods enemies, and ſometimes for the delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of his People. Thus you ſee what kind of Earthquake is here meant, and what it ſignifieth.</p>
               <p>But let us look a little further into it, and compare it with other Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes in this book of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> which we may call Apocalyptical Earthquakes, of which we find five.</p>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. The firſt at the opening of the ſixth Seal, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.12.</item>
                     <item>2. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond at the opening of the ſeventh Seal, <hi>Rev.</hi> 8.5.</item>
                     <item>3. The third in my Text, near the concluſion of the ſixth Trumpet.</item>
                     <item>4. The fourth at the ſounding of the ſeventh Trumpet, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. laſt.</item>
                     <item>5. The fifth at the pouring out of the ſeventh Vial, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.18.</item>
                  </list> Among theſe, this in my Text is the middlemoſt; the two firſt (like the two laſt) fall in quickly, the one after the other, the firſt under the ſixth, the ſecond un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſeventh Seal, a little before the ſounding of the firſt Trumpet; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which we meet with no more Earthquakes till the cloſe of the ſixth Trumpet in my Text, which long interval takes up above a thouſand years, during all which time the Earth ſeemeth to ſtand ſtill, not ſimply, but in compariſon with what is now like to be at the cloſe of the ſixth Trumpet, and the beginning of the ſeventh. The world is now drawing towards its end, that its ſhaking fits do come ſo faſt upon it; and ſome more than ordinary Change is haſting upon the World; for there have been great Changes in it during the long Interval aforeſaid, and yet none of them have been called Earthquakes, as this here in my Text, which though it falls only upon <hi>the tenth part of the City,</hi> yet it is a fair warning to all the other parts, and a ſure Pledge of their approaching ruine.</p>
               <p>The far greater part of this Interval between the ſecond and third Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake, hath been taken up with the Reign of the Beaſt and of the <hi>Turk,</hi> who in all this time have met with no ſuch conſiderable Change, as now they are warned to look out for, and which ſhall ſhortly befall them under the ſeventh Trumpet; but as for the change ſignified by the Earthquake in my Text, it appertains eſpecially to the Beaſt who ſlew the Witneſſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The ſame hour there was a great Earthquake.] Great;</hi> Let us conſider that a little, and compare it with the other four Earthquakes; For they are all great, and as it ſeemeth, greater than this here in hand.</p>
               <p>The firſt, mentioned, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.12. is expreſly called <hi>a great Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake,</hi> and ſurely greater than this in my Text; For that was ſo great, that it ſhook the whole <hi>Pagan</hi> Empire, and overthrew it <hi>funditùs,</hi> with an utter deſtruction, as in the Verſes there following. It overthrew the <hi>Pagan</hi> Emperial world, the Heavens thereof, the Sun, Moon, and Stars thereof, and every Mountain and Iſland belonging thereunto,<note place="margin">Rev. 6.12.—to the end.</note> and all the perſons therein, from the King to the Bond-ſlave. This then was a dreadful Earthquake, which ſhook and overthrew the whole fabrick of the Heatheniſh Empire, and introduced a bleſſed Change as to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:59095:19"/>world,<note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 8.2.</note> at leaſt for a ſeaſon. But now, as for the Earthquake in my Text, though it is great, yet nothing near ſo great, as ſhaking only and overthrowing a tenth part of the great City. Only know thus much, that it will deſtroy the Heavens, the Sun, and Moon, and Stars of this tenth part, and overturn the little world therein. For all the Apocalyptick Earthquakes overthrow Worlds; the firſt the Roman <hi>Pagan</hi> world, the ſecond the Roman <hi>Chriſtian</hi> World, the third, fourth and fifth the Romiſh <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> World; after which ſucceedeth the Millenary World, which the Apoſtle calls, <hi>The World to come,</hi> H. <hi>br.</hi> 2.5.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As for the ſecond Earthquake at the opening of the ſeventh Seal, and immediately foregoing the ſounding of the firſt Trumpet,<note place="margin">Rev. 8.5.</note> this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo was a great Earthquake, though it is not expreſly ſo called. For,
<list>
                     <item>1. A great Change followeth it, as appeareth in the eighth and ninth <hi>Chapters.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. Whereas there are ſeveral expreſſions of Terrour when it comes, as, <hi>Voices, and Thunderings, and Lightnings, and an Earthquake,</hi> there ſeemeth to be a gradation in the words, and the ſoreſt diſpenſation brings up the rear, and that is an Earthquake. So that this alſo looks greater than that in the Text in hand.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Compare the Earthquake in my Text with the next to it, under the ſeventh Trumpet, and though this here is great, yet that is great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, ſo as it is not in my Text.
<list>
                     <item>1. Becauſe accompanyed with Lightnings, and Voices, and Thunderings, and great Hail.</item>
                     <item>2. Becauſe it is the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate fore-runner of thoſe Vials which ſhall utterly deſtroy the Beaſt. Whereas the Earthquake in my Text ſhakes only a <hi>tenth part of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and makes way for the ſeventh Trumpet.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Compare it next with the Earthquake at the pouring out of the ſeventh Vial, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.18. And though this in my Text is called <hi>great,</hi> yet that is greater, and indeed the greateſt that ever was. For mark what the Text ſaith of it: <hi>There were Voices, and Thunderings, and Lightnings, and there was a great Earthquake, ſuch as was not ſince men were upon the Earth, ſo mighty an Earthquake, and ſo great; and the great City was divided into three parts.</hi> This Commotion and concuſſion made the great City to fall aſunder; <hi>And great</hi> Babylon <hi>came into re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance before God, to give unto her the cup of the wine of the fierceneſs of his wrath; and every Iſland ſted away, and the mountains were not found, and there fell upon men a great hail out of Heaven, every ſtone about the weight of Talent, &amp;c.</hi> Well therefore may it be ſaid, <hi>There was not ſo great an Earthquake ſince men were upon the earth.</hi> For now alſo the Romiſh Antichriſtian world is wholly deſtroyed, and the Mille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary introduced. For in theſe three laſt Earthquakes, it is obſervable, that there is a gradation, that in my Text is exceeded by that, <hi>verſe</hi> laſt, and this exceeded abundantly by that under the ſeventh Vial, which is the ſweeping and concluding Earthquake.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:59095:19"/>
               <p>And in theſe two laſt, it is obſervable again, that they are accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with Hail, the firſt of them with <hi>great hail,</hi> but the laſt with ſo great, that every Stone is about the weight of a Talent, big enough to brain an Oxe or an Elephant; for God now knocks down not only the great Beaſt, but the <hi>Turk</hi> and Devil alſo. And now, not only the Earth ſhakes under the Beaſt, but the Heavens alſo from above diſcharge (as I may ſay) their Cannon-ſhot, ſuch maſſy Hail-ſtones as God hath reſerved againſt this day of battel and war, and now is fulfilled what is written, <hi>The windows from on high are open, and the foundations of the earth do ſhake, Iſa.</hi> 24.18. It will be now in the end of this Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an World, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the end of the Old World, when the deep from beneath, and the Windows of Heaven from above, met together and conſpired to deſtroy that world of the ungodly. Thus I have opened to you theſe five <hi>Revelation Earthquakes,</hi> comparing that in my Text with the other four, as the leaſt of them all, yet called <hi>a great Earthquake,</hi> conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered ſimply in it ſelf, as alſo effecting a great work, in throwing down the tenth part of the great City.</p>
               <p>Let us come now to the effect of this Earthquake in the following words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And the tenth part of the City fell.]</hi> By <hi>City</hi> here we underſtand the <hi>great City</hi> ſpoken of, <hi>ver.</hi> 8. For this verſe referrs to that, though that is called <hi>the great City,</hi> this only <hi>The City,</hi> without the Epithete <hi>Great,</hi> yet not without an Article or two, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which amounts to as much as <hi>Great,</hi> for it is, <hi>That tenth part of that City;</hi> ſo that both the City it ſelf and its tenth part, have a ſingular remark here upon them. But what is <hi>that City,</hi> that <hi>great City?</hi> It is not a mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial City properly ſo called, compaſſed about with walls, but the City here being the ſame with that <hi>ver.</hi> 8. is the whole Juriſdiction and Government of <hi>Rome.</hi> And whereas it is ſaid, <hi>The tenth part thereof fell, viz.</hi> with the foreſaid Earthquake, this cannot be meant of the City of <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf, which is reſerved for the fifth Vial, which I conceive will not be poured out till after the ſounding of the ſeventh Trumpet. And though a Learned Interpreter of the <hi>Revelations</hi> expoundeth this of the City of <hi>Rome,</hi> which he ſaith, is now but the tenth part of what <hi>Rome</hi> was in former times, I ſuppoſe that will not eaſily be proved. Nor is this tenth part (as I humbly apprehend) to be underſtood Geographically, for a tenth proportion of the Romiſh Dominion; but I rather conceive, that it is to be underſtood Myſtically, for one of the ten Horns; among which <hi>Great Brittanny</hi> is reckoned one, and by ſome, the firſt.</p>
               <p>But why doth there fall no more of the City than the tenth part?<note place="margin">Queſt.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Not but that it were juſt with God to deſtroy the whole City,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> which hath fully deſerved it long ſince; but God begins only with a tenth part to give the remainder of the City fair warning, leſt all be ruined (as it will) after ſome time longer. You know, this City is ſpiritually
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:59095:20"/>called <hi>Sodem, ver.</hi> 8. Now God gave <hi>Sodom</hi> a timely Admonition by the Conqueſt which the four Kings had over it, and the ſpoil which they got therein, and the captivating its Inhabitants; and when this prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not to amend them, after a while it was utterly deſtroyed: Even thus it is with this <hi>Spiritual Sodom</hi> in my Text.</p>
               <p n="2">2. I further anſwer, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>God hath a revenging eye;</hi> The eye of divine Vengeance is not ſo much at time this of the Earthquake upon the whole City or Power of <hi>Rome,</hi> as upon that part thereof where the Witneſſes were ſlain.</p>
               <p>But the whole City is guilty of this Internetion and Witneſs-ſlaughter:<note place="margin">Ob.</note> For though the hands of multitudes, and of the the far greater part by much of all the Citizens of the Romiſh Polity, were not in this ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, yet their hearts do fully conſent unto it; like as in the <hi>French</hi> Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacre, <hi>Aug.</hi> 24. in the year 1572. though the blood was ſhed in <hi>France,</hi> yet <hi>Rome</hi> did even triumph when they heard thereof.</p>
               <p>This is granted,<note place="margin">Sol.</note> according to that of Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.35. as alſo <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.20. But divine Vengeance falls here upon the Principals, and Patience forbears the Acceſſaries for a ſeaſon longer, giving them ſpace, as yet, to repent. For in all the ſtrokes and plagues that God inflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth upon the Beaſt, God ſtill expecteth Repentance, as we plainly ſee, <hi>Rev.</hi> 9. laſt; and, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.9, 11. This fall or ruine then lighteth one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon the place or Countrey where the ſlaughter of the Witneſſes is committed, to give warning to the remainder of the City, which yet ſuffereth alſo in the fall of this tenth part.</p>
               <p>But how and in what manner doth this tenth part of the City fall,<note place="margin">Queſt.</note> it may be ſaid?</p>
               <p n="1">1. By dreadful Concuſſions;<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> as if God ſhould ſay, <hi>I will overturn, overturn, overturn it.</hi> God will throw down the Props and Pillars thereof with notable ſubverſions.</p>
               <p n="2">2. There will alſo be (as I am apt to think) a <hi>falling,</hi> by <hi>falling off;</hi> in the end, or <hi>falling away</hi> of this tenth part from the remaining nine, by them that ſhall ſurvive the overthrow; for I do not think that the tenth part ſhall be utterly deſtroyed. The ſurvivers ſhall deſert the Beaſt and his Worſhip and Government. So that the whole City ſhall be mulcted and fined a tenth part, paying the tithe of it ſelf to divine Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance for the ſlaughter of the Witneſſes; for the Hierarchical Power ſhall from thence forward ceaſe in that Countrey, which but now was the tenth part of the great City, and the Countrey ſhall be forfeit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for its bloodſhed, into the hands of our Lord Jeſus. My appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions are, that it will be ſuch a fall as this, <hi>i. e.</hi> which will end in a falling off, and that ſuch a Change will be introduced by this Earthquake, as will prove to be a great Judgment upon the great Whore. The Hierarchy exerciſed in that tenth part ſhall fall and ſink, and never
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:59095:20"/>riſe again, like as what is ſunk by an Earthquake never riſeth more, but is for ever buryed in its own ruines. A City or Town may be ſhaken by a little Earthquake, and yet not fall, though it may ſtand tottering and hang a-to-ſide, and be propt up for a time, but this here is ſaid to be <hi>a great Earthquake,</hi> which will quite ſwallow up that which before was only ſhaken and ſhivered, that now it ſhall never riſe again.</p>
               <p>It may be ſaid, perhaps, That what the Sea loſeth in one place,<note place="margin">Ob.</note> it gaineth in another:</p>
               <p>But it is not ſo with the Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sol.</note> which now falls into that irreco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verable Conſumption propheſied of, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.8. <hi>The Lord ſhall conſume that wicked one with the breath of his mouth;</hi> i. e. with the Goſpel, which ſhall now begin to flouriſh, when the tenth part of this City is fallen. When the City begins to fall, the Goſpel ſhall begin to riſe in equal proportion, and never fall again. There will be no Balm for this bruiſe, no Cordial for this Conſumption; the great Whore ſhall now begin to abate of her fleſh, by that time that this Earthquake hath done reckoning with her; her Arm ſhall be ſo broken, that there ſhall be no Roller to bind it that it may be healed and ſtrengthned. And thus you have heard the firſt Effect of this Earthquake opened; the next followeth.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>And in the Earthquake were ſlain of men ſeven thouſand.</hi>] The New Tranſlation rendreth it, <hi>Capita hominum, heads of men:</hi> The Old, <hi>Nomina hominum, Names of men,</hi> and ſo the Original hath it; the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whereof is, by an Hypallage, <hi>Men of Names,</hi> i. e. famous men. The <hi>Grecians</hi> (I ſuppoſe) borrow the expreſſion from the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> who call eminent and renowned men, <hi>Men of names,</hi> as you may ſee, 1 <hi>Chron,</hi> 5.24. and 12.30. The Text there compared with the Margine in your Bibles, where <hi>Men of names</hi> in the Hebrew are called <hi>famous men</hi> in the Text. And hence, <hi>men of no name</hi> in the Hebrew, are called, <hi>baſe men</hi> by the Tranſlators, <hi>Job</hi> 30.8. By this then you ſee the meaning of the expreſſion in my Text; for theſe ſeven thouſand men of Names, are <hi>Viri nominati,</hi> as <hi>Junius</hi> and <hi>Tremelius</hi> render the ſame word, <hi>named,</hi> or <hi>famous men.</hi> They are therefore men of eminency and fame, as if one ſhould ſay, Dukes, and Earls, and Lords, and Knights, and Eſquires, and Gentlemen, and Prelates, and Judges, and Counſellours, and Doctors, and Collonels, and Captains, and Magiſtrates, Officers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now of theſe men of Names, there are ſlain in this Earthquake ſeven thouſand, <hi>i. e.</hi> very many, Seven being a number of perfection, and often uſed in this Book of the <hi>Revelations;</hi> as ſeven Spirits, ſeven golden Candleſticks, ſeven Seals, ſeven Trumpets, ſeven Angels, ſeven Vials; ſo here, <hi>ſeven Thouſand, i. e.</hi> a great number. And of theſe it is ſaid, That they were ſlain in the Earthquake, the Spirit of God (perhaps) alluding to ſuch an effect of natural Earthquakes, as when they throw down Towns or Cities, and bury many of the Inhabitants in the ruines.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:59095:21"/>
               <p>For this here is called <hi>a great Earthquake,</hi> and therefore whenever and wherever it comes, there will be a terrible ſhake both of Perſons and Things, <hi>viz,</hi> Houſes, Inhabitants, Lands, Goods, Moneys, Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances, Callings, Trade, Liberty, Health, Relations, Life, and many other Comforts; Mens hearts will ſhake, fear and tremble, and ſome perhaps will cry to Rocks and Mountains. It maketh me to think of the caſe of the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 14.15, 16.</note> when God committed them among themſelves, and when they ſheathed their Swords in one anothers bowels; there was a trembling (ſaith the Text) in the hoſt, in the field, and among all the People, inſomuch that the Garriſon and the ſpoilers alſo trembled, and the Earth quaked, ſo that it was a very great trembling, (or, <hi>a trembling of God</hi>) and the multitude melted away, and they went on beating down one another. Such a kind of Earthquake peradventure it may be, when the Mighty man, and man of <hi>Name,</hi> ſhall ſtumble againſt the mighty, and both fall down together. Briefly; It will be ſuch a ſhake as will make a man to eat his bread with quaking, and to drink his water with trembling and with carefulneſs, as ſometimes the Prophet did, <hi>Ez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k.</hi> 12.18. At what time, the Sword ſhall devour fleſh, and be drunk with the blood of the ſlain from the beginning of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venges upon the Enemy. And when ſhall this be? Upon the back of the Witneſſes Aſcenſion, when once a Reformation (on their part) riſeth upon their riſing; for then, and not till then, will this Earthquake be; which yieldeth ſome matter of Comfort to the People of God, that they are ſo well prepared againſt ſuch a ſhaking time; for now that they are drawing nearer to God, he will be their ſtrong Tower to which they ſhall run and be ſet aloft. Wherefore, though the Heavens and the Earth ſhall ſhake, the Lord will be the hope of his People, and the ſtrength of the Children of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> So much for this Effect of the Earthquake.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And the remnant were affrighted.</hi>] This is the third Effect of it. <hi>The Remnant;</hi> Here is Mercy in the midſt of Judgment, that all in this tenth part of the City are not ſlain, a remnant liveth and eſcapeth. God is ſo far here from deſtroying the whole City, that he deſtroyes not all the Street. But yet <hi>the Remnant are affrighted,</hi> flying, like as the People fled from the Earthquake in the daies of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah, Zach.</hi> 14.5. Or as the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> that were round about the Tents of <hi>Korah</hi> and his Company fled when the Earthquake ſwallowed up the Rebels, ſaying, <hi>Leſt the Earth ſwallow us up alſo,</hi> Numb. 16.34.</p>
               <p>This is the caſe of this <hi>Remnant,</hi> who are not ſimply afraid, but <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted,</hi> and e'en at their wits end; they are not ſlain with the Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake, but almoſt kill'd with fear, yet ſpared and have their lives given them for a prey. God might juſtly have deſtroyed the whole Street where his Witneſſes were ſlain, and lay dead, but he is ſatisfied with the Sacrifice of the lives of Seven thouſand <hi>men of Names,</hi> and it is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:59095:21"/>what a conſiderable price; for if ſo many men of Names fall, how many thouſands of little or no name are ſlain together with them? As <hi>Aha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuerus</hi> ſaid to <hi>Eſter; The Jews have ſlain five hundred men in</hi> Shuſan <hi>the Pallace, and the ten ſons of</hi> Haman; <hi>what have they done in the reſt of the Kings Provinces?</hi> But God's Eye is eſpecially upon the Fatlings and the beſt of the Flock, that they may be offered up in ſacrifice to him, and it is ſomewhat like his ſacrifice in <hi>Bozrah,</hi> and his ſlaughter in the Land of <hi>Idumea,</hi> where his ſword is filled with blood, and made fat with fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, with the blood of Lambs and Goats, and with the fat of the kid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys of Rams, when the Unicorns come down with them, and the Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locks with the Bulls, in the day of the Lord's Vengeance, and the Year of Recompences for the controverſies of <hi>Zion, Iſa.</hi> 34.6, 7, 8. And it is alſo conſiderable, that what is wanting in the Number of the ſlain, is made up in the fall of the Tenth of the City; a part only are ſlain, but the whole City falleth in a degree.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>And they gave Glory to the God of Heaven.</hi>] This is the laſt Effect of the Earthquake. But how do they give God glory?
<list>
                     <item>1. By confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their Sins, eſpecially in ought that they did relating to the ſlaying of the Witneſſes. <hi>My Son</hi> (ſaith <hi>Joſhua</hi> to <hi>Achan</hi>) <hi>give glory to the Lord God of Iſrael, and make confeſſion unto him, Joſh.</hi> 7.19.</item>
                     <item>2. They repent alſo of the ſins which they confeſs; for therein alſo is God glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.9.</item>
                     <item>3. They give God the glory of his Patience and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der mercy in ſparing them, and plucking them as a brand out of the burning, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.22.</item>
                     <item>4. They glorifie his Juſtice and righteous deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings with the bloody Street, ſaying, <hi>Thou art righteous, O Lord, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou haſt judged thus, for they have ſhed the blood of Saints and Prophets, and of thy Witneſſes, and thou haſt given them blood to drink, for they are worthy; Even ſo, Lord God Almighty, true and righteous are thy judgments.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list> And this glory is given to the <hi>God of Heaven,</hi> as in my Text, <hi>i. e.</hi> to the true God; for as <hi>Cyrus</hi> ſaith in his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation of liberty to the <hi>Jews, The God of Heaven, he is the God, Ezra</hi> 1.2, 3. The <hi>Remnant</hi> is now convinced of their former Atheiſms, Superſtitions and Idolatries, <hi>and give glory to the God of Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But is this Acknowledgment extorted from them,<note place="margin">Queſt.</note> or is it freely given by them, as by ſuch whoſe hearts are now unfeignedly turned to the Lord?</p>
               <p>It is apprehended by ſome,<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> that it is done by the power only of a ſtrong Conviction in the time of this great Judgment and Vengeance of God upon his Adverſaries, but not done by ſuch whoſe hearts are now truly turned to the Lord: For the Judgments of God do ſometimes wring ſuch acknowledgments from wicked men, as when <hi>Pharaoh</hi> could ſay after the plague of the Hail, <hi>I have ſinned this time, the Lord is righteous,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 9.27.</note> 
                  <hi>and I and my people are wicked.</hi> And as <hi>Joſhua</hi> ſaid to <hi>Achan, My ſon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joſh. 7.19, 20.</note> 
                  <hi>give I pray thee glory to the Lord God of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and make confeſſion unto
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:59095:22"/>him; And</hi> Achan <hi>ſaid, Indeed I have ſinned againſt the Lord God of</hi> Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, <hi>and thus and thus have I done.</hi> See alſo <hi>Judg.</hi> 1.7. and 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 12.6. and 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.5. But others do apprehend that this Remnant here were effectually wrought upon by this terrible hand of God, and gave glory to him in ſincerity. But I find no reaſons given for either opinion, yet I incline to this ſecond. If indeed this Remnant were ſuch as had been totally immerſt and drenched in Popery, I ſhould have been of the firſt opinion; for the Jurats and ſworn Creatures of the Man of ſin, cannot repent to give glory to God whatever judgments are inflicted on them, as you may clearly ſee, <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.20, 21. and 16.9, 10, 11, 21. The Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Popery is a Spirit of dedolence and impenitency, becauſe the complete Worſhippers of the Beaſt are noted as obſtinate Reprobates, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.8. and, 14.9, 10.</p>
               <p>This Remnant therefore were only ſprinkled and dipt a little into Popery, and ſuch may and often do repent of their Idolatries and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions. And by this you ſee that there is a poſſibility that this rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant may truly repent and give Glory to the God of Heaven. Yea, and it is probable that they do effectually repent in giving Glory unto God.</p>
               <p>For it is here ſaid, that a <hi>tenth part of the City fell</hi> by this Earth-quake; now, How did it fall? Two wayes, as hath been ſaid;
<list>
                     <item>1. A part therereof fell by being Slain, as a juſt recompence for Slaying the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, upon whoſe aſcenſion it immediately followeth.</item>
                     <item>2. The remnant alſo of the tenth part fell, but how? By falling away from the Power and Dominion of the Beaſt.</item>
                  </list> For if they had ſtill perſiſted in their former courſes and adhered to the Beſtian Intereſt, the tenth part of the City had not fallen by falling away, becauſe a remnant had ſtill ſtood their ground. And this kind of falling, by falling off, was alſo a Righteous Judgment of God upon the Beaſt, whoſe Power is hereby diminiſhed; for the <hi>Remnant</hi> throws off the Papal Hierarchy, never to be reaſſumed more by them; and God is pleaſed to preſerve them (as with ſubmiſſion I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive) to make uſe of them for future againſt the Beaſt and his Intereſt; Perhaps it is the firſt of the ten horns which ſhall hate the Whore, and make her Deſolate and Naked, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Surely this remnant is reſerved for for ſome ſingular purpoſe, ſeeing they are ſnatcht thus out of this dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ruine; for they related unto them that were Slain, in that they are called their <hi>Remnant;</hi> It ſeemeth therefore as if God intended to turn them into an Horn wherewith to goar and wound the Beaſt.</p>
               <p>This Street then is, from the time of this Earthquake, and ſo forward, for ever cut off from the great City, and being now purged, partly by Divine Vengeance on the bloody men of Names, and partly by the repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the Remnant, it is thenceforth conſecrated unto the Government of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Remnant</hi> then is reſerved,
<list>
                     <item>1. As a Trophy of Victory and Triumph.</item>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:59095:22"/>
                     <item>2. For ſome ſignal Service to be performed afterward by them under the ſeventh Trumpet, which followeth quickly upon the back of this Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake, as you may ſee, <hi>v.</hi> 14.</item>
                  </list> And thus I have opened (as God hath holpen this paſſage of the Earthquake and the ſeveral effects of it.</p>
               <p>But now it may be inquired,<note place="margin">Queſt.</note> what may be the cauſe of this <hi>great Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake?</hi> As the Pſalmiſt ſaith, <hi>What ailed ye, O Mountains, that ye skiped like Rams, and ye little Hills like Lambs?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You know what follows in anſwer hereunto;<note place="margin">Anſw.</note> 
                  <hi>Tremble thou Earth at the Preſence of the Lord, at the Preſence of the God of</hi> Jacob. It comes to paſs therefore from the Preſence of God among his People, coming down to viſit the Street where his Witneſſes were Slain.<note place="margin">Deut. 21.15.—</note> When under the Law a man was found ſlain in the Field, and it was not known who ſlew him, the City that lay next unto the ſlain Man was to purge it ſelf from that blood, and the Elders thereof were to come and waſh their hands over a ſlain Heifer, and to ſay, Our hands have not ſhed this blood, neither have our eyes ſeen it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> God is tender of the Lives of men, eſpecially of the lives and blood of his Saints which is precious in his ſight, and he will certainly make inquiſition for it in due time, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 9.12. And when he goes about this act of Juſtice, what will he do to that City, or to that Street, where his Witneſſes are found ſlain; not ſlain (I ſay) in a Field by unknown hands, but in the open Street, yea, and by them that dwell therein, and who cannot thus waſh their hands? He will call them to a ſevere account, For there is a cry in the Ears of God for Vengeance.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In the general, There is a cry of many and great ſins in the Streets, for where ſuch a ſin is committed as Witneſs-ſlaughter, ſurely there are many other crying ſins. Now the ſins of a land may lye ſo heavy upon it, that they may make it to ſhake and even to reel and rent again, like as a Cart may be ſo heavy loaden, that it may make the very Axle-tree to crack, and quite overturn all.<note place="margin">Iſa. 24.19, 20.</note> 
                  <hi>The Earth</hi> (ſaith the Prophet) <hi>is utterly broken down, the earth is clean diſſolved, the earth is moved exceedingly, the earth ſhall reel to and fro like a drunken man, and ſhall be removed like a Cottage.</hi> Why, what is that which preſſeth it down ſo greatly? It fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth; <hi>And the tranſgreſſion thereof ſhall be heavy upon it, and it ſhall fall, and not riſe again.</hi> It muſt needs be a marvellous weight that makes the Earth thus to move, yet ſuch is the weight of ſin.</p>
               <p n="2">2. More particularly, there is the cry of blood in the Street, as I have ſaid; and it is the cry of the blood of the Witneſſes. For though they are not literally ſlain, <hi>i. e.</hi> not as men, but as Witneſſes, yet the Lord calls it, and accounts it a ſlaughter, yea, and their very enemies account them as naturally dead; and they are greatly Oppreſſed, Vexed, and Silenced, Impriſoned, Impoveriſhed, and cruelly handled, and ſo, that it haſteneth alſo the Death of ſome of them,<note place="margin">Jer. 2.34.</note> and reacheth alſo to the blood (as I may ſay) of many thouſands of Souls who depended upon
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:59095:23"/>their Miniſtry; and ſuch blood hath a loud cry in the ears of God, and ſuch a cry will ſhake the Earth wherever the ſin is committed, and remains un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purged. You know how the Martyrs under the fifth Seal cryed with a loud voice,<note place="margin">Rev. 6.10, 12.</note> ſaying, <hi>How long, O Lord, holy and true, doſt thou not Judge and Avenge our blood on them that dwell on the Earth?</hi> What then followeth? <hi>And I beheld when he had opened the ſixth Seal, and lo, there was a great Earthquake,</hi> &amp;c. You have heard before of the greatneſs of that Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake, and how it ſhook and quite overthrew the whole Roman Pagan Empire.<note place="margin">2 King. 24.4.</note> You know alſo that the blood ſhed by <hi>Menaſseh</hi> could not be expiated by the greateſt reformation that was ever wrought, but the whole Land of <hi>Judah</hi> was at laſt ſhaken to pieces for it. That land is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly deplored that lyeth under the guilt of blood, eſpecially of ſlaying Chriſt's Witneſſes. See 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 36.15, 16. It layed <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> houſe, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Temple, deſolate, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.37, 38.</p>
               <p>And when the <hi>Jews</hi> killed the Lord Jeſus,<note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 2.15, 16.</note> and the Prophets, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted the Apoſtles, forbiding them to Preach to the Gentiles that they might be ſaved, they filled up their ſins, and the Wrath of God came up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them to the uttermoſt. This is a filling and a finiſhing ſin; even Reformation it ſelf (were it equal to <hi>Joſiah</hi>'s) cannot ſave that land from a great Earthquake, and from ſuch Vengeance as will make the ears of them who hear it to tingle. What ſaith the Prophet? <hi>The City ſheddeth blood in the midſt of it, that her time may come; thou art become guilty in thy blood, and haſt cauſed thy dayes to draw near, and art come even to thine years.</hi> Ezek. 22.3, 4.</p>
               <p n="3">3. There is yet another cry, and that is from the Prayers of God's people, eſpecially from under their Affliction. No doubt but the cries, and ſighs, and groans of the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in <hi>Egypt</hi> were accompani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with many Prayers, and it brought ſuch vengeance upon <hi>Egypt,</hi> as you have ſcarce read the like. God never forgets the cry of the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 9.12.<note place="margin">Exod. 22.23.</note> 
                  <hi>If but a poor Widdow or Fatherleſs child be afflicted, and they cry at all unto me, I will ſurely hear their cry, ſaith the Lord.</hi> And know thus much, that the Prayers of one diſtreſſed Child of God may be ſuch, that they may ſhake the very Earth it ſelf. What ſaith <hi>David? In my diſtreſs I called upon the Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 18.6, 7.</note> 
                  <hi>and cryed unto my God; He heard my voice out of his Temple, and my cry came before him, even into his ears; Then the Earth ſhook and trembled, the Foundations alſo of the Hills moved and were ſhaken, becauſe he was wroth,</hi> &amp;c. The Prayers of <hi>David</hi> in his diſtreſs ſhook Heaven, Earth, and Sea. And wherefore is it that God ſaith, <hi>I will ſhake the Heavens, and the Earth, and the Sea, and the dry land, and I will ſhake all Nations, and the deſire of all Nations ſhall come?</hi> I ſay, wherefore is this, and whence proceedeth this great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſion? Even from the deſire of all the Saints that live among the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the world. They are oppreſſed and perſecuted in the world, and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:59095:23"/>they cannot be quiet; upon this they cry out, and utter their deſires, <hi>O that Jeſus Chriſt would come and deliver us, and plead our cauſe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve us in our diſtreſſes, and call the world to a reckoning! Even ſo come Lord Jeſus, come quickly.</hi> I tell you, This will coſt the world a ſound ſhaking. Little do people imagine what the force of God's peoples prayers is, they have an Earth-ſhaking power in them. The praying Saints are a thundering Legion. <hi>Samuel</hi> no ſooner cryeth to the Lord,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 7.10.</note> but he heareth him and anſwereth him with a dreadful diſcomfiting thunder upon the <hi>Philiſtines.</hi> And when the Saints fall to prayer at the cloſe of the ſeventh Seal,<note place="margin">Rev. 8.3.5.</note> preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly follow <hi>Voices, and Thunderings, and Lightnings, and an Earthquake.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 4.31.</note> When <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> were returned from their perſecutors to their own compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,<note place="margin">Act. 15.25.</note> they betake themſelves to prayer, which was no ſooner ended but the place was ſhaken, where they were aſſembled together. And when <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> prayed and ſung praiſes to God in the priſon, and in the ſtocks, ſuddenly (ſaith the Text) there was a great Earthquake, and the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of the priſon were ſhaken, and immediately all the doors were opened, and every ones bonds were looſed, and the Keeper of the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon drew his Sword and would have killed himſelf. And do we think now, that all the prayers that have been made within theſe few years by the Saints in the world, will not end in a dreadful Earthquake? God hath already anſwered his people, and will again anſwer them, by ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible things in righteouſneſs. Thus you have ſeen the procuring cauſes of this Earthquake. I ſhall conclude with ſome Conſectaries, Informations and Exhortations flowing from what hath been opened to us.</p>
               <p n="1">1. By what we have heard in the Explication of this thirteenth verſe, we have a further proof of what ſometime I ſaid, That the Witneſſes are ſlain not in all parts of the great City, but in ſome one eminent Street thereof that hath not quitted and caſt off the power of the Beaſt; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I thus argue:</p>
               <p>Where the revenge of God is inflicted for the ſlaying of the Witneſſes, there, and there only, are the Witneſſes ſlain:</p>
               <p>But the revenge of God is not inflicted upon the whole City for the ſlaying of the Witneſſes, but only on a tenth part thereof:</p>
               <p>Therefore in that tenth part thereof, and there only, are the Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſlain.</p>
               <p>For God proportioneth his Revenge unto the place of the ſlaughter, making it commenſurate and adequate thereunto, and doth not exceed the bounds thereof.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In this diſpenſation we may ſee the ſingular patience of God towards the Enemies of his Witneſſes, in that he doth not preſently bring this great Earthquake upon them; they may meet with many a ſore concuſſion, during the time of the ſlaughter, and preſently after it is over; but yet God deferrs the terrible Earthquake till the aſcenſion of the Witneſſes, and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:59095:24"/>till that great Voice from Heaven hath ſaid unto them, <hi>Come up hither,</hi> and that they have aſcended in a Cloud in the very ſight of their Enemies. Which (by the way) ſheweth us plainly, as I touched it before, that this loud voice and call unto them to aſcend, doth not proceed from the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Rulers of this World, as ſome have thought, for theſe are <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,</hi> and the <hi>men of names,</hi> who are to be ſlain in the Earthquake pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently upon the Aſcenſion of the Witneſſes. They continue Enemies unto the very time of their deſtruction.</p>
               <p>But that which I am ſpeaking to, is the Patience of God towards that Street where the Witneſſes are ſlain; for God doth not deſtroy the <hi>men of names</hi> ſo ſoon as they have ſlain the Witneſſes, no, nor ſo ſoon as the Witneſſes are riſen and ſtanding upon their feet; He tarrieth till they are aſcended, and gives his Enemies warning enough; but when once the Aſcenſion time is over, and Reformation of Churches, Families, and Saints on foot, the Earth will forbear ſhaking no longer; there is then but an hour (<hi>i.e.</hi> a very ſhort time) between the Aſcenſion and the Earthquake.</p>
               <p n="3">3. We are ſhewed the juſt Revenge of God upon theſe Enemies, in that he <hi>ſlayeth</hi> them, a meet recompence for their ſlaying of the Witneſſes. Thus,<note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 13.10.</note> 
                  <hi>he that leadeth into Captivity, ſhall go into Captivity,</hi> and, <hi>he that killeth with the Sword, ſhall be killed with the Sword.</hi> So here, They that ſlay, ſhall be ſlain; as it is written,<note n="†" place="margin">Gen 9.6.</note> 
                  <hi>He that ſheddeth blood, by man ſhall his blood be ſhed.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Jer. 51.56.</note> 
                  <hi>The Lord God of Recompences ſhall ſurely requite;</hi> he is as punctual in his Juſtice, as powerfull in his Patience.</p>
               <p n="4">4. In that the holy Ghoſt here ſeemeth to allude to the manner of great. Earthquakes, which is to ſwallow up houſes and their Inhabitants, ſo as <hi>Korah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram</hi> were ſwallowed up, though that was ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the Earth renting, than quaking, yet ſwallowed up they were,<note n="*" place="margin">Numb. 16.32.</note> they and their houſes and all the men that appertained to them, and their goods; I ſay God ſeemeth to deal with theſe <hi>men of names,</hi> as with thoſe Rebels and their companions; As if God ſhould ſay, they ſhall periſh in the gain-ſaying of <hi>Kore,</hi> and as ſo many <hi>Dathans</hi> and <hi>Abirams,</hi> and Rebels againſt the God of Heaven; for ſuch God accounteth theſe, whatſoever theſe accounted the Witneſſes.<note n="*" place="margin">Numb. 16.2.</note> And of theſe three men it is ſaid, <hi>They roſe up before Moſes, with certain of the Children of Iſrael, two hundred and fifty Princes of the aſſembly, famous in the Congregation, men of renown.</hi> They were, juſt like theſe in my Text, <hi>viri nominatiſſimi,</hi> men of great note and name; and ſo Mr. <hi>Aynſworth</hi> tranſlateth the word <hi>famous,</hi> in that place, <hi>Men of names,</hi> and he reckoneth them no leſs than States-men, as you may ſee in his Expoſition. And the like title alſo is given to the oppreſſing Gyants of the old World, whoſe foundation was over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowed with a Flood;<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 6.4.</note> They are called <hi>Mighty men,</hi> and men of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown.</p>
               <p>You ſee then the account of God concerning theſe famous ones in my
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:59095:24"/>Text; They ſlay the Witneſſes as Rebels, and ere long themſelves are ſlain of God, as ſuch.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Whereas theſe many thouſands were <hi>men of Names,</hi> it may denote (as Mr. <hi>Brightman</hi> obſerveth from the expreſſion) that God doth not fall blindfold with his judgments upon men; he doth not ſtrike <hi>Andaba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarum more, ſed certo, nominatimque,</hi> even ſo certainly and knowingly, as if he named theſe great men; There's for you, ſuch a one, ſaith he, and there's your reward, ſaith he to another, naming him, &amp;c. <hi>God ſhall ſhoot at them with an arrow, ſuddenly ſhall they be wounded,</hi> Pſal. 64.7. He doth not ſhoot like that <hi>Syrian</hi> who hit <hi>Ahab</hi> at adventure, but he aim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth alwayes when he ſhooteth, and never miſſeth the mark.</p>
               <p n="6">6. God then is no reſpecter of perſons;<note n="*" place="margin">Job 34.19.</note> 
                  <hi>He accepteth not the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Princes, nor regardeth the Rich more than the Poor..</hi> Nay, he hath a ſpecial eye upon the <hi>men of Names,</hi> for you muſt know that this Earthquake here doth ſlay many a man, hundreds and thouſands no doubt <hi>nullius nominis,</hi> of no name or fame at all, but theſe you ſee are not here mentioned, but only the <hi>viri Nominum,</hi> the men of great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown. And God will do this dreadfull Execution upon them by a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable hand from Heaven; for Earthquakes are in a ſpecial manner from God, there is no hand of man in them. <hi>The mighty ſhall be taken away without hand,</hi> Job 34.20. That is, without the hand of any man; God will do it by an out-ſtretched hand from Heaven.</p>
               <p n="7">7. It is very obſervable, That in Gods execution of Judgment here, he falls moſt eminently upon the principal Ring-leaders, the <hi>men of Names,</hi> whoſe hands eſpecially were employed in ſlaying the Witneſſes. Many others of little or no <hi>name</hi> were ingaged alſo in the ſlaughter, but the men of Names ſtirred them up and ſet them on work, and led them the way alſo by their Examples and Authority. Wherefore God takes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of <hi>them</hi> eſpecially, and the ſtroke falls moſt remarkably upon <hi>them</hi> as the great Oppreſſors of the Witneſſes, and hinderers of Reformation. He takes off theſe therefore, and removes them out of the way, as intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now to bring in Reformation <hi>contra gentes viroſque nominum,</hi> againſt all oppoſition whatſoever. For great men, if not alſo good, are great oppoſers of that which is good; as God ſometimes ſaid to <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him five and twenty of his great Enemies, and among them <hi>Jaazaniah</hi> and <hi>Pelatiah</hi> Princes of the people; <hi>Son of man,</hi> ſaith God, <hi>Theſe are the men that deviſe Miſchief and give wicked Counſel in this City; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore propheſy againſt them, Ye have multiplied your ſlain in this City, and ye have filled the Streets thereof with the ſlain,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>I will execute judgments upon you, and ye ſhall fall by the Sword,</hi> &amp;c. And ſaith <hi>Ezekiel, It came to paſs when I propheſied, that Pelatiah dyed,</hi> Ezek. 11.1. — See alſo <hi>Numb.</hi> 25.4.</p>
               <p>Thus when the ſixth Seal was opened, and that the Judgments of God
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:59095:25"/>fell moſt formidably upon the Roman Pagan Empire for the moſt horrid bloody Perſecutions uſed againſt the Chriſtians, the moſt righteous God began with the ring-leaders, the <hi>viri nominum</hi> are ſet in the front of the Sufferers, <hi>viz. The Kings of the Earth, and the great men, and the rich men, and the chief Captains, and the mighty men;</hi> and after them come in the men of <hi>ſmall names, every bondman, and every freeman, Rev.</hi> 6.15. The Earthquake there mentioned ſhook all the Empire from the higheſt to the loweſt, but it began with, and fell heavieſt on, the <hi>men of Names, Kings, great men, rich men, chief Captains, and Mighty men.</hi> For as for the Bondmen and Freemen, they were ſet on by their Kings, and great men, and rich men, and chief Captains, and mighty men; That is, the Informers, and Catch-poles, and Jaylors, and poor Souldiers, were but as a company of boudmen to the Kings, great men, and men of Names; and they muſt do what the Powers will command them, but (you ſee) that will not excuſe them when the Earthquake cometh; but yet the Grandees are the men in the Van that are moſt eminently ſhaken and thrown down thereby; they ſhall pay for it to the purpoſe.</p>
               <p n="8">8. We may here behold the riches of God's grace, that he not only ſpareth a Remnant of his, and his Witneſſes Enemies, that they are not ſlain with the reſt in the Earthquake, but he giveth to them alſo the grace of repentance. They might have drunk of the ſame Cup with thoſe men of renown, as being <hi>a Remnant</hi> of them, eſpecially as to their enmity, but God lets them live to repent and give him glory. I ſuppoſe theſe to be ſuch as were perſecutors as well as thoſe others, but they did it ignorantly in unbelief, and therefore they obtain this mercy; perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture the other (at leaſt many of them) are ſuch as tranſgreſs of malicious wickedneſs, and rebell againſt the light, which is a very high provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. They are nothing like ſo ignorant as malicious and deſpighthful, being deſperate ſworn enemies to Jeſus Chriſt, his People, Cauſe and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt. Yet even the ſpared Remnant are bad enough, as known and profeſſed enemies to the God of Heaven, to whom now they give glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, whoſe glory and honour they never cared for before. O the riches of the glorious grace of God, that he ſhould ſave ſuch as theſe, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from the deſtruction of the Earthquake, but of Hell it ſelf! Let us exalt this ineſtimable grace, and believe, love, and praiſe, and give glory to the God of Heaven for their ſo doing; and in the mean while, let none deſpair, when ſuch men as theſe repent.</p>
               <p n="9">9. They that are the People of God and dwell in that bloody Street, may have hopes, that God will not utterly deſtroy it, ſeeing there is a Remnant that will be ſpared, which ſhall be as the ſhaking of an Olive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree and the gleaning of Grapes after the vintage; is ended. You know what devaſtation God maketh by his four ſore Judgments, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 14.22. And yet ſaith the Lord, <hi>A remnant ſhall be left, and they ſhall come forth
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:59095:25"/>unto you, and ye ſhall ſee their way and their doings, and ye ſhall be comforted concerning the evil that I have brought upon you.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 6. <hi>ult.</hi>
                  </note> God will not u utterly forſake that Street, but yet in it ſhall be a tenth, and it ſhall return, and ſhall be eaten as a Teyl-tree, and as an Oak, whoſe ſubſtance is in them when they caſt their leaves; for ſo the holy ſeed ſhall be the ſubſtance thereof. God will as it were tithe this tenth part, and conſecrate it and the land unto himſelf for ſome ſignal and ſingular ſervice to his Name. And as God will deſtroy the Microcoſm and little world in that land by this Earthquake, <hi>viz.</hi> the Sun, Moon, Stars, and Heavens and Earth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; ſo he will create new Heavens (as I may ſay) and a new Earth therein, and the former ſhall be remembred no more.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, We ſee what a ſhaking world we live in; Let our hearts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hang looſe to the things of this world, to which they are ſo apt to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here. How ſoon God may ſhake us, we know not, and ſhaking (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of the earth) is in order to the removing of the things that are ſhaken, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.26, 27. And when men are ſorely ſhaken, they had not need to take hold on things that ſhake, and which are ready to remove away from under them; they have need to lay hold on ſtable and abiding things that will ſtand faſt and not forſake them. If any ſhould ſay, This ſhaking may be far enough off from us; Let no man think ſo; For admit that this be not the time nor place ſpoken of, in <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.7, 8. Yet where there is any thing like it, there will be that alſo which is as like unto this Earthquake.<note place="margin">Ezek. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3.10, 13.</note> What ſaith the Lord to <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiel? If a righteous man beget a ſon that is a robber, a ſhedder of blood, and that doth the like to any one of theſe things,</hi> viz. there ſpoken of, <hi>he ſhall not live, he ſhall ſurely dye, his blood ſhall be upon him. That doth the like,</hi> &amp;c. He doth not ſay, <hi>That doth the very ſame.</hi> If an Hue and Cry purſue after a ſhedder of blood, and find a man that is very like him, and apprehend him upon ſuſpition, and it falleth out upon examination that the perſon apprehended hath alſo ſhed blood in like manner, though he is not the perſon that ſhed the blood inquired after, yet he ſhall not live, he ſhall ſurely dye, his blood ſhall be upon him: Even ſo, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> God will never put up the ſlaying of his Witneſſes, though (perhaps) it may not be that ſlaying here ſpoken of, but only the like unto it. There is no ſatisfaction to be taken for the life of a murtherer, nor is there any City of Refuge appointed in the law for him,<note place="margin">Numb. 35.31.—Deut. 21.1.-10.</note> he muſt be taken away from God's altar, or ſlain at it, as <hi>Joab</hi> was, otherwiſe, the whole land lyeth under the guilt of blood.</p>
               <p>You know what <hi>Hanun</hi> did to <hi>David</hi>'s Embaſſadors, who were ſent to him in meer love and good will. He did not ſlay them, but ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully abuſed them.<note place="margin">2 Sam. 12.30, 31.</note> O how was the land of the children of <hi>Ammon</hi> ſhaken for this abuſe! The Kings crown was taken from his head and ſet on <hi>David's,</hi> the <hi>Ammonites</hi> ſlain, <hi>Rabbah</hi> ſacked and plundered, and the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:59095:26"/>people of the Land put under ſawes, and harrows, and axes of iron, and made to paſs thorow the brick-kiln. And yet, what is this abuſe of <hi>David</hi>'s Embaſſadors, to that of Chriſt's, which we have lived to ſee? And what will the Lord then do, how dreadfully will he avenge the high and horrible contempt of his Meſſengers? Prepare therefore for times of great concuſſions; perhaps they may prevent ſome of your deaths, if not prove alſo the cauſe of them. Hang looſe (I ſay) to the world, and be in the number of the aſcenders, get up above the Earth, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach nearer unto Chriſt in Reformation and Holineſs, and then, if the worſt ſhould come, you may ſing <hi>Luther's</hi> Pſalm, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 46. And be not ſo ſollicitous about the Earthquake, as about the Aſcenſion that imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately precedeth it; for the Earthquake muſt come, but wo be to them when it comes who are not got above the Earth. It is the great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God to defer the Earthquake till after the Aſcenſion, for the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſafety to his people; which I conceive to be a ſpecial reaſon why it is deferred till then; though another may be, That a foundation may be layd for the carrying on the work of Reformation the better, when the Earthquake is at an end.</p>
               <p>And it promiſeth well to the Street, that God will not utterly deſtroy it, nor take away his Goſpel from it;
<list>
                     <item>1. In that he ſtill continueth his Witneſſes in it.</item>
                     <item>2. Becauſe Reformation and Holineſs are aſcending when the Earthquake cometh.</item>
                  </list> Now therefore let it be the care and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the People of God,
<list>
                     <item>1. To <hi>riſe.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. To <hi>aſcend.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. To <hi>riſe;</hi> what is that? To hold forth the Spirit of Life from God; They muſt walk in oppoſition to their ſlain condition; now, they were ſlain by the loſs of ſpiritual life, courage, and activity; therefore they muſt riſe by a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Spirit.</item>
                     <item>2. Let it be their endeavour alſo to <hi>aſcend, i. e.</hi> to reform, <hi>viz,</hi> Churches, Families, Hearts and Lives.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>And if we muſt thus aſcend, then it will follow, that we muſt not ſtay at that pitch of Reformation to which we have already attained, but muſt yet get up higher; there is a great deal more yet to be done. For per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps ſome may ſay, Are we not aſcended already? No; we are not yet come to the utmoſt of our Reſurrection, which (as we have heard) is gradual. True; there hath been a kind of riſing and aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of late years; for wherefore are the Witneſſes ſlain, but for their climbing up ſo high in their Seperations and Profeſſions? And yet (you ſee) they muſt aſcend up higher; For we are not riſen up ſo high above former times, as we muſt yet riſe up higher above our preſent ſelves; God will not be ſatisfied with our Reſurrection when it is come to its ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt degree, but then he requireth alſo an Aſcenſion, which will be gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual likewiſe, unto the time of the pouring out of the ſeventh Vial.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:59095:26"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
